<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A testimony of love and good vvill unto all them who desire to come to enjoy an everlasting being with the Lord of life when dayes in this world will have an end. Given forth by one that desireth the good of all, and that none may perish in sin, John SOnghurst.</title>
            <author>Songhurst, John, d. 1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 145 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60911</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4687</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220752</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832144</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832144</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36615</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60911)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36615)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2135:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A testimony of love and good vvill unto all them who desire to come to enjoy an everlasting being with the Lord of life when dayes in this world will have an end. Given forth by one that desireth the good of all, and that none may perish in sin, John SOnghurst.</title>
                  <author>Songhurst, John, d. 1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>67 [i.e. 86] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 3 reads: A few words to all people, who desire to come to enjoy an everlasting beeing with the Lord of life, when dayes in this world will have an end.</note>
                  <note>Many pages misnumbered; page 86 misnumbered 67.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Friends House Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  England --  Pastoral letters and charges --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36615:1"/>
            <p>A TESTIMONY OF LOVE AND GOOD VVILL Unto all them who Deſire to come to Enjoy an Everlaſting BEING with the Lord of Life, when Dayes in this World will have an End. Given forth by one that deſireth the Good of all, and that none may Periſh in Sin, <hi>John Songhurſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Theſ. 5.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Prove all Things, and hold faſt that which is Good.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:36615:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:36615:2"/>
            <head>A few Words to all People, who deſire to come to enjoy an Everlasting Beeing with the Lord of Life, when Dayes in this World will have an End.</head>
            <p>TIME in this World is very ſhort, and it is very Uncertain when the End of it will come, and yet nothing more Certain than the End of it to come; but the World that is to come is for evermore, which is called, <hi>A Long Home,</hi> becauſe it will never have an End;<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.5.</note> and it will be to all People either Joy or Torments forever and ever.</p>
            <p>Now the World to come conſiſts of two Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances, unto which all muſt go: the Righteous to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of Eternal Life, &amp; Glory, &amp; Endleſs Felicity with God, and the Wicked into the Lake that burns, prepared for the Devil &amp; his Angels; the one an End<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Joy, the other an Endleſs Miſery and Diſconſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with Weeping Wailling and Gnaſhing of Teeth: Though true it is, <hi>That the God of Heaven never Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated Man nor Woman, and left them without Remedy, with intent, that they ſhould go into the Place of Torment, of which there is no End; No: But he Created them for a Purpoſe of his own Glory; intending, that they ſhould have continued with himſelf in Paradiſe, where they ſhould never have had Pain, Trouble or Sorrow, but Joy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36615:3"/>End.</hi> This was God's Love to Mankind in the Beginning, when he Created Man in his own Image, in which Image man ſtood Single, Pure, Holy, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Sin, or Fault in the Sight of God; and in that Condition the Lord made a Covenant with Man, and gave him Liberty to eat of every Tree of the Garden,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.9.</note> except one (to wit) The <hi>Tree of Knowledge of Good and Evil;</hi> but the Lord told <hi>Adam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>If he did eat of that Tree, he ſhould ſurely Dye.</hi> Now here came in the Flood of Miſery upon all the World, that is, Man and Woman not keeping to God's Command, nor believing what God had ſaid to them; for if they had kept in the Faith, then had they been preſerved from him that enſnared them; for the Devil had an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to Enſnare <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> and came to them with a Lye,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.6.</note> and told them, <hi>They ſhould not Dye,</hi> if they did eat of the Fruit of the Tree that God had told them they ſhould not eat of, but <hi>That they ſhould be as Gods,</hi> which was ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lye: And believing more what the Serpent ſaid, than what God had ſaid unto them, they ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to brake Covenant with God; for if they had not believed what the Serpent ſaid more than what God had ſaid, but had kept the Faith of God, they had not been enſnared by the Serpent: and thus the Serpent having diſputed the Woman out of Faith in God, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed that in her, he created a falſe Faith of his own, which before could not have been done: And here came in the firſt believing of Lyes; and ſo to this day, <hi>wo be to that Soul that doth not believe that God Means as he Speaks.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:36615:3"/>
            <p>Thus looking more at the Preſent Enjoyment of the Thing preſented, than at the ſad Effect it would produce, and letting go the Belief of what God had ſaid to them, to believe a Lying Promiſe from the Serpent, they became not contented with God's Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance, but hearkned to the Serpent, Proudly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to come to an Higher Attainment than the Lord had placed them in; ſo the Woman looking upon the Fruit to be pleaſant and beautiful to the Eye, and good for Food, did eat of it; though the Lord had warned them before-hand, and told them, <hi>That in the Day they did eat thereof,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>they ſhould Dye,</hi> which the Woman did remember: Thus they let go the Faith, cloſed with the Serpent, and broke Covenant with God; here they came to loſe that Glorious Image, in which they were Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and that Liberty, Soul-peace, Fellowſhip and Unity with God, and ſpiritual Bleſſings and Benefits which they enjoyed before: And ſo by Diſobedience to God Sin entered into Mankind, and Man was taken Bond-ſlave by the Devil, and Captive to his Will: And ſo, according to God's Unalterable Word, and Unchangeable Decree, who ſaid unto Man, <hi>In the Day thou eats thereof,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>thou ſhalt ſurely Dye,</hi> Man dyed to Righteouſneſs, which will be mans Miſery forever, if not deeply Repented of before he go hence, and through Repentance come to dye to Sin, and live to God.</p>
            <p>And God hath alſo decreed, That in that Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on man fell into by that Act of Diſobedience, by which Sin entred, and man became ſeparated from
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36615:4"/>God his Maker, and ſhut out of his Kingdom, that no Man nor Woman in that Sinful Eſtate ſhall again ever enter into his Kingdom, till they come to know them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Freed from Sin again, and ſo to be ſeparated from the Evil of the World: For inaſmuch as our firſt Parents, <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> did commit Sin, and ſo Sin entred, and by Sin they came to ſhame, and to be rejected of God; and from that day, to this day, Sin reigned over all Men and Women by Corrupt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and Death by Sin from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and from <hi>Moſes</hi> to this Day; and ſo all by this Nature <hi>Children of wrath,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>We, as well as others:</hi> So is it certain, that in this State all are undone for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing it is concluded, That Sin hath entred all men, and all have ſinned, and that all are at a loſs, concerning the Knowledge of God, his Way, and the Salvation of their Souls; and that none ſhall be Heirs of God's Kingdom, while they remain in the Sinful Nature, becauſe while men live in that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, there is no Salvation; and if no Salvation, then Damnation: Then the <hi>Queſtion</hi> that remains is this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seeing theſe Things are ſo, how ſhall People be Freed from Sin, and from Condemnation, and the Wrath to come, and be made Heirs of God's Kingdom, and Injoyers of his Salvation, and Inheriters with them that are Sanctified?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord ſeeing this hath provided a Means (to wit,<note place="margin">John 1.1.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt, the true Light</hi>)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36615:4"/>being much grieved for Man in that loſt Condition he was plunged into, for he was become a Bond-ſlave to the Devil, and an Enemy to his own Soul, and no way capable of Salvation without God, though the Fault was in Man; <hi>For God created him a Noble Vine, wholly of the right Seed;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 2.21.</note> 
               <hi>but he became a degenerate Plant of a ſtrange Vine,</hi> and Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt God his Maker: Yet (I ſay) the Lord in the riches of Mercy, and great Pity towards the Sons of Men, did bear with them, and did not cut them off in their Sin, neither deſired he their Death or Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but rather that they ſhould turn from their Wickedneſs and live. And ſo, the Lord conſidering the Miſery man was fallen into, and what was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of man, looking down upon them with an Eye of Pity and Compaſſion, remembred his former Love to man in the Beginning, when he firſt created him, how that he had more regard to man than to all he had created upon the Earth beſides, inſomuch that he made him in his own Likeneſs, in pure Holineſs, without any Spot of Sin, and ſet him above the Ox &amp; the Aſs, and above all other Creatures in Wiſdom, Power and Glory; but man loſing that Dominion God gave him, fell under the Ox and the Aſs (that is) became more degenerated than the Beaſt of the Field, and hath not Power of himſelf over Sin, that holy Nature being loſt, which he was created in; that Wiſdom, that Glory, that Power, in which he was created, are alſo loſt, and Man diſabled to glorifie God; but the Beaſt of the Field kept their places, as they in the firſt were created, and praiſe the Lord in their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36615:5"/>kind, and he findeth no Fault in them: And as man at the firſt was ſet above them, ſo now in God's Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count he is ſet above man in his Fallen State: for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, If one have an Ox or an Horſe to a Pond to drink, and beat him, till one kill him, he will drink no more but to do him good; but man is worſe than a Beaſt in drinking to Exceſs, and ſo drinks up Iniquity as an Ox drinks Water; and many times men deſtroy their Bodies, as well as their Souls, in Exceſs of Drunkenneſs: and as we are in this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, the Beaſts of the Field are ſet before us; and herein Complaint was taken up againſt Man: The Lord by the Mouth of his Prophet ſaid,<note place="margin">Iſaiah 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>He had nouriſhed, and brought up Children, and they had Rebelled againſt him, and had for ſaken him Dayes without Number, (Him, the Fountain of living Mercyes to their Souls) and had been ſeeking and inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to themſelves other Fountains, which would ſtand them in no stead;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>broken Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterns that would hold no water:</hi> And in this Condition the Beaſt of the Field is ſet before man; and the Lord ſaid, <hi>The Ox knows his Owner,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>and the Aſs his Maſters Crib, but</hi> Iſrael <hi>doth not know the Lord.</hi> Oh, the Sad and Deplorable State of Man! Oh, the depth of Miſery that men are fallen into! whom God ſo highly honoured, that now the poor Ox and Aſs is ſet before them! Oh! what Miſery, Wo, Dread, Sorrow and perpetual Deſtruction (never to have End) doth attend Man and Woman in this Condition, and that without Remedy of fallen man!
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36615:5"/>had not the Lord in Mercy towards man provided a Remedy, we had been all Undone, as on the account of Salvation, and that forever.</p>
            <p>But the Lord of yearning Bowels and tender Mercy to our Souls, hath preſcribed a way how Man may come again into favour with God, and to eſcape all thoſe fore-mentioned Dangers, which by reaſon of Sin they are like to be plunged into, and become more Miſerable than any other Creature upon Earth; for there is nothing elſe that God hath Created upon the Earth but Man and Woman, that hath ſinned; therefore in this Condition they are of all other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures moſt miſerable in the ſight of God: And the Lord looking down upon People in this Condition, &amp; ſeeing them all gone aſtray, and that there was none in this ſtate did good, no, not one; but all were run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Head-long to Hell, being gone from the Wiſdom of God, and the good Spirit of God in themſelves; therefore there was none found doing good: and then came they to be led by a bad Spirit: And to this day the bad Spirit rules and bears ſway, more or leſs in all People that are not come to obey Chriſt's Spirit, and to be led and guided by it: For all People upon the Earth are led and guided by one of theſe two Spirits: Sinners by the Spirit that begetteth Sin in them, and carrieth it on in Thoughts, in Words and in Actions; and Righteous men by the Spirit of Righteouſneſs, that begetteth Righteouſneſs in them, and carrieth it on in them in Thoughts, Words and Actions, and thus all men and Women come to be known, that is, by their Words and Actions, what Spirit it is they are
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36615:6"/>led by;<note place="margin">Mat. 12.33.</note> 
               <hi>For the Tree is known by his Fruit,</hi> as Chriſt ſaid of old.</p>
            <p>Now here was the Lord's Love wonderfully mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſted again to Mankind, after he had rebelled againſt God, and had loſt that glorious Habitation which the Lord had placed him in, in that the Lord was not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to reject man forever, and to take the Kingdom from him forever, but upon Terms the Lord offered it to man again, and hath ſent his good Spirit into the Wilderneſs of deep Diſtreſs,<note place="margin">Nehem. 9.20.</note> whither Man and Woman was driven from the Preſence of God, by reaſon of Sin, to viſit man in his fallen ſtate, and bring him back again to God. Now this is the Terms that God hath proffered his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to man again upon;<note place="margin">Luke 13.3. Acts 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>Repent ye, and Believe the Goſpel:</hi> And this Jeſus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed in his Meſſage from the Father, when he ſent him into the World to preach the Glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidings of the Kingdom. So all that turn again to God, believe him, and hear him, and obey his Voice, as the true Shepherd, and Repent of the Evil they have done,<note place="margin">Iſa. 1 17.</note> and ceaſe to do Evil, and turn from their Evil Wayes, and learn to do well, and lead a new Life, and keep God's holy Laws and Commands the reſidue of their Lives.</p>
            <p>Now to all, without Reſpect to Perſons, Rich or Poor, Old or Young, High or Low, Bond or Free, Maſter or Servant, White or Black, All that will receive God's Kingdom upon theſe Terms, behold, it ſtands offered to them: and to help man in this Work, ſeeing no man can do it of himſelf without God's help,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36615:6"/>
               <hi>God hath ſo loved the World, that he hath ſent his Son, Chriſt Jeſus, the true Light,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>that Enlightens every man that cometh into the World,</hi> to viſit man, and hath given a Meaſure or Manifeſtation of his good Spirit to every Man, and to every Woman to profit withal,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.7.</note> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Sayings of the Scriptures of Truth, which we that are called <hi>Quakers</hi> do own to be <hi>A True Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Holy men of God, and of thoſe things that ought to be Believed and Practiſed.</hi> And this profiting which they are to profit by the Meaſure of his holy Spirit is upon the Account of Salvation, which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe can do, but God's Light and Spirit; and therefore he hath freely given it to all People to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken them out of Sin and Wickedneſs, ſaying, <hi>Ariſe and go hence, for this is not your Reſt.</hi> He alſo makes Proclamation of Liberty to the Captives that are in Satans Bands, That they may all upon theſe fore-mention'd Terms come to Enjoy Peace with God again, and a Crown of Everlaſting Life to their Souls when Dayes in this Life will have an End,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.7.</note> when all Crowns of Glory here below will fade away, and never be enjoyed more; Oh! then Happy will they be that have got an Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in God, and an Inheritance that will never decay.</p>
            <p>And God alſo by his holy Spirit makes Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on the other hand, That they that will not turn to him, and lead a New Life, but ſtill Rebel againſt the Manifeſtations of his Light, and the Strivings of his good Spirit in their own Hearts and Conſciences, till he leaveth ſtriving with them, and their Day of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36615:7"/>be over, That unto all ſuch, and upon all ſuch ſhall paſs the Sentence of,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.23. ch. 25.40.41.</note> 
               <hi>Go you Curſed, Depart from me, I know you not:</hi> And thus the Wicked, and all the Workers of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity will be turned into Hell, and all that forget God, where they muſt inherit Everlaſting Puniſhment. And here is the <hi>Reprobation</hi> &amp; <hi>Damnation</hi> that God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed in the Beginning; not that God would not have ſaved them. But it is happened to them as to <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> of old;<note place="margin">Luke 13.34.</note> God hath ſtriven to gather them, and they would not be gathered; and ſo God's Unalterable Decree in Juſtice is fulfilled upon them.</p>
            <p>And this concerneth all people upon the face of the Earth, that deſire Peace with God in this Life, and a Dwelling with him for their Souls when this Life will have an End: I ſay, It concerns them to ſearch and try how it is with them, and how they ſtand in Relation to the Spirit of God in themſelves, and to conſider by what they are led; for all are led by the good Spirit or the bad; and the good Spirit leads Peoples Mind Heaven-wards, to mind heavenly things; and the bad Spirit leads Peoples Minds Hell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, to mind Ungodlineſs, and Carnal Earthly things; and if not reſiſted, ſtrived againſt and turned from, it will lead into the Bottomleſs Pit, out of which there is no Redemption. And no man in his own Will or Strength can ſtand againſt that Soul-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying Spirit, which hath taken hold of all Mankind, ſo that without the help of God's Spirit all are undone being no way able to Help themſelves; but bleſſed be the Lord, he hath taken care of man, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36615:7"/>hath ſent his good Spirit to that end to help us againſt the Spirit of Unrighteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>Now here all People by this good Spirit of God may come to have their Underſtandings opened, and to ſee how it is with them, as upon the account of their Salvation, and how they ſtand in acceptance with God. Now Mark, here lies the thing, if thou art led by the Spirit of God, then thou art at Peace with the Spirit of God in thy ſelf;<note place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note> but if the Spirit of God be yet a Reprover and Condemner in thy Heart and Conſcience,<note place="margin">John 16.7, 8. John 3.3, 20, 21, 22.</note> and check and trouble thee there, then thy Peace and thy Salvation is not wrought with God, but thou ſtandeſt far rejected in the ſight of God, who is the Searcher of all Hearts, and the Diſcerner of all Thoughts, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thou mayſt profeſs much of Religion, and mayſt run into many Inventions and Forms, thinking to pleaſe God, and to find Peace for thy Soul; and thou mayſt Pray, Preach, Read and Sing, and be an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of outward Ordinances, and Family-Duties too, as they are called, and yet be an Enemy to God and to thy own Soul, if thou refuſeſt to be led by the Spirit of God out of the Evil Wayes of the World, from a vain Converſation;<note place="margin">Prov. 15.8. &amp; 28.9.</note> 
               <hi>For the Prayers of the Wicked are an Abomination to the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For ſo far came <hi>Saul</hi> when he was an Enemy to God and his People, and to his own Soul, he made a great flouriſh about Religion, and was much in the outward Obſervations:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 9. &amp; chap. 22.</note> he ſaid of himſelf, that he was blameleſs as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36615:8"/>the outward Law;<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he had great Learning, and was very zealous for Religion (far beyond Thouſands now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes of thoſe that are called <hi>Chriſtians</hi>) yet all this while he was an Enemy to the Spirit of God in his own Heart, and in his blind Zeal kickt againſt the prickings of Gods Spirit in himſelf, as many high Profeſſors do now adayes, and are rebelling againſt the ſtrivings of Gods Spirit in their own Conſciences, while full of outward Duties, that make a fair ſhew in the Fleſh: But it is hard for People to kick againſt the Pricks; for conſider, that if ever man come into the Way of God again, it muſt be by being inſtructed by the Spirit of God;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.23.</note> 
               <hi>For the Reproofs of inſtruction are the Way of Life:</hi> and God hath given his good Spirit to that end, <hi>viz.</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct People in the way of Everlaſting Life.</p>
            <p>And this is he that was in that Body of Fleſh that ſuffered at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by the murdering <hi>Jews,</hi> who was the only begotten of the Father,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 1.12, 13, 14. Chap. 3.16.</note> full of Grace and Truth, that whoſoever would believe on him, ſhould not Periſh, but have Everlaſting Life.</p>
            <p>He that ſaid, <hi>Before</hi> Abraham <hi>was I am,</hi> this is that ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 8.59.</note> that quickning Spirit, who is that Saviour and God manifeſted in Fleſh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.5.</note> who is come to Redeem people out of Sin, and from a Vain Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that he might be the Saviour of their Soul,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.13, 14.</note> by inwardly waſhing and cleanſing them from their Sin by his own Blood; and not to ſave People in Sin, but from it: and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36615:8"/>this is that <hi>Rock</hi> that followed <hi>Iſrael</hi> of Old, of which they drank; <hi>Which Rock,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4.</note> ſays <hi>Paul, was Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So here is the means of Salvation, and that of Gods preparing, for poor loſt mans recovery, to bring him back to be an Inheritor in that Kingdom that ſtands in Righteouſneſs, and Peace, and Joy forever; and the way to it, is to come to be inſtructed by this holy Spirit of Truth, which leads into all Truth, and the Reproofs of this inſtructing Spirit is the way to Life; as the Scriptures of Truth ſay and bear Teſtimony.</p>
            <p>Now that that Reproveth people for ſinning, is that which leadeth them that adhere to it out of Sin, and Inſtructs and teaches people the Way to this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, and till People come to own the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, Teachings and Leadings of this good Spirit of God, that leads into all Truth, and teaches all Truth, and no Lye is in it; they ſhall never know the way to the Kingdom of Heaven, nor have the Peace of it. (never any did) But by rejecting the ſtrivings of Gods Spirit, and ſtriving againſt the prickings of it in the Conſcience comes Miſery upon all People. This was the Overthrow and Ruin of <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old (<hi>Neh.</hi> 9.20.) That God had given unto them his good Spirit to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them, but they rebelled againſt it, till their Day was over, and then came in a Flood of Miſery upon them, and then all the World could not help them, but his Wrath broke out upon them, as it is written, <hi>Their Carcaſes fell in the Wilderneſs,</hi> yea <hi>Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Three Thouſand in one day,</hi> and were <hi>deſtreyed of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents and of the Deſtroyer,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.8, 9, 10, 11, 12. and this happened to them becauſe they rebelled againſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36615:9"/>God's good Spirit, that he gave to inſtruct them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting it till their Day was over, and that the Lord ceaſed ſtriving with them, and ſwore in his Wrath <hi>They ſhould not enter into his Reſt;</hi> a diſmal Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion!</p>
            <p>Theſe things did not only happen to them in that time, but to all thoſe in all Ages that rebelled againſt God's Spirit, till he ceaſed ſtriving with them, they ever came to Miſery, which never will have an End.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rebellion</hi> (ſaid one of old) <hi>is as the Sin of Witchcraft,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.23. and the Law would not ſuffer a Witch to live: and as in the time of the Law God allowed not Witches their natural Lives, neither will God give Eternal Life to thoſe Souls that go on in Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the Reproofs of his good Spirit now, but ſin out the Day of their Viſitation, even the Day of his Long ſuffering and Forbearance to them, who hath ſaid, <hi>My Spirit ſhall not alwayes ſtrive with Man, Gen.</hi> 6.3. It was the Saying of a good Man in dayes paſt, ſpeaking to People in their Youth, one that was acquainted with the Dealings of the Lord with Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; <hi>Remember thy Creator in the dayes of thy Youth, before the Evil Day come</hi> (Eccleſ. 12.1.) that is the Evil Day, when God's Spirit hath done ſtriving with Man, which will come upon all People that do not turn at the Reproofs of God's Spirit in their Hearts in that time when he offereth Merey to them.</p>
            <p>But in all Ages God raiſed up faithful men, that were faithful to the Spirit of God in themſelves, to bear a Teſtimony againſt Sin, and to warn People of the Evil of their Doings, as well as by the ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36615:9"/>of his good Spirit in them, becauſe he would leave them without Excuſe, that hated Knowledge, and did not chuſe the Fear of the Lord, but ſet at nought all his Counſel, and would not turn from their Evil Wayes at the Reproof of his good Spirit in them. And theſe good Men the Prophets, they ſpake what God ſpake to them, or in them, by his Spirit, and not a Premeditated Matter, as the Prieſts do now adayes (of all ſorts) that are not led by the Spirit of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>In dayes paſt God ſpake to the People by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and they were moved to ſpeak as he pleaſed, ſometimes little, and ſometimes much, as he pleaſed, and what hep eaſed; and in this manner God ſpeaks by his Prophers in this our Age; and theſe be the true Miniſters, and none elſe, nor none elſe ever were; nor can any inform men, and ſet them in the Way to Heaven, if they are not themſelves led, inſtructed,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. &amp; Chap. 2.10. 1 John 1.1, 2.</note> taught and guided by the Spirit of God themſelves; ſuch can inſtruct others as God doth them; and ſuch can ſpeak their Experience to the People of the Teachings, Leadings and inward Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of God's Spirit, and how the Soul comes to be reacht, converted and brought into Union, Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and Fellowſhip, and to converſe with God, as they are moved by the Holy Ghoſt, and as the Spirit gives them utterance; and theſe be the true Miniſters of Chriſt and theſe preach without Study or Natural Art or Invention of Man; and they that take upon them to be Teachers of others, and are not come to be taught, led and guided themſelves by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36615:10"/>of Truth, that leads [mark] into all Truth, that ſo by this they may turn people (as Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles did of old) to the Leadings and Guidings of God's Spirit in themſelves, are Falſe Prophets and Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; for <hi>that which may be known of God is manifeſt and to be manifeſted in man; for there God ſhews it to man,</hi> as it is written, <hi>God hath ſhewed it unto them,</hi> Rom. 1.19. And all that take upon them to be Teachers, and would ſeem to be ſomething, and know not theſe things, are Deceivers, and will cheat people of their Souls, and have done many Thouſands already. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 14.14.23.28, 29, 30, 31, 32, 36.</p>
            <p>And this I ſpeak that all may take Warning, and be awakened to ſeek after God, and come out from the Falſe Prophets and Deceivers that are in the World, and in wardly to wait upon God, to receive from him the Spirit of Wiſdom and Revelation in the Knowledge of himſelf in your inward parts; and this is the ſaving Knowledge, as it is writterr; <hi>This is Life Eternal, to know thee the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent,</hi> John 17.3.</p>
            <p>But now to return to the thing before in hand, which was, to take a View of the Miſery, Deſtruction and Ruin of thoſe that in their Day did not turn from the Evil of their Doings at the Reprooſs of God's Spirit in their own Hearts and inward parts, but provoked God from day to day, then God raiſed up his Servants the Prophets, and ſent them to warn Evil-doers, as a Sign to them, that the Long-ſuffering of God was drawing to an End, and that his Spirit ſhould ceaſe ſtriving with them, and that ſwift Deſtruction ſhould come upon them, except a ſpeedy Repentance and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36615:10"/>Amendment of Life; as namely, <hi>Noah,</hi> that juſt Man, who walked with God, and was perfect in his Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, him did God raiſe up to be a Witneſs againſt that Generation (a Miniſter, a Preacher of Righteouſneſs) to whom God revealed his Mind concerning that Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, ſaying, <hi>My Spirit ſhall not alwayes ſtrive with Man</hi> (that will take no Warning) and God ſaid to <hi>Noah, Make an Ark, for the End of all Fleſh is come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me; and behold I, even I</hi> (ſaid God) <hi>bring a Flood of Water to deſtroy all Fleſh, wherein is the Breath of Life: but I will eſtabliſh my Covenant with thee; for thee have I ſeen Righteous before me in this Generation.</hi> And I ſuppoſe much need not be ſpoken now to convince people, that God did deſtroy the old World in the execution of his Wrath, and that becauſe they ſinned out the Day of their Viſitation, and did not Return at God's holy and juſt Reproofs, while his Spirit ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with them.</p>
            <p>Again, the Inhabitants of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> with their Cities and Subſtance, for their Sins were brought into Aſhes, who as the Figure of Eternal Vengeance hath God made to be an Example to all that afterward ſhould live Ungodly here.</p>
            <p>Alſo, there was the Overthrow of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt, who in the Pride of his Heart ſaid, <hi>Who is the Lord, that I ſhould obey his Voice? I know not the Lord, neither will I let</hi> Iſrael <hi>go.</hi> This Sturdy Oak did God viſit with Judgment, by pouring out of his Plagues upon him and his Land; and he brought down his Pride in the Red Sea, and he Humbled him by a perpetual Overthrow in the Deep: but this <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> whom <hi>Pharaoh</hi> would not let go, that they might hold a Feaſt unto the Lord in the Wilderneſs, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36615:11"/>Sacrifice unto their God, them did God deliver out of his hand by a ſtrong Arm, and led thorow the Red Sea, as upon dry Land, making the Waters ſtand as Walls on the Right hand, and on the Left. And thus God made <hi>Pharach</hi> an Example to all that after ſhould be Hard-hearted, and refuſe to Obey the Lord.</p>
            <p>And let it never be forgotten, that in all theſe Overthrows God took care for the Righteous, for them that loved God, and obeyed his Voice, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled not againſt his good Spirit, but turned at the Reproofs thereof, who ſinned not, but ſtood in Awe, as Namely, <hi>Noah,</hi> that Righteous man, him God ſaved from the Deſtruction of the old World, and delivered juſt <hi>Lot</hi> out of the Overthrow of <hi>Sodom;</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> his People he redeemed out of the Iron-Furnace, and delivered them from <hi>Pharaoh</hi> that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt them, and pleaded their Cauſe with the Kings of the Earth, and avenged their Wrongs upon them.</p>
            <p>Yet here's one Preſident more; that part of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which ſinned, and obeyed not God's Voice, but day by day provoked him to Anger by their Rebellion and Unbelief (even them for whom God had wrought ſuch great Salvation) God overthrew in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, and cut them off in his Anger by the Sword, the Plague, or other Deſtruction, and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty three thouſand fell in one day, and God made their Children to wander in the Wilderneſs Forty Years, to bear the Whoredoms of their Fathers, till the Carcaſes of their Fathers were conſumed in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs: Theſe God was grieved and diſpleaſed with, becauſe they rebelled againſt his Good Spirit, which he gave them to inſtruct and lead them in the Way
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36615:11"/>they ſhould go; and this was not all, but he ſware in his Wrath, <hi>They ſhould not enter into his Reſt:</hi> So may we well conclude with the Apoſtle, That if God ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not the Angels that ſinned, nor the Old World that ſinned, nor the Cities of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> that ſinned, nor <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt that ſinned, nor that part of <hi>Iſrael</hi> that ſinned, whom God ſo dearly loved, and wrought ſo great Salvation for, but made them Examples for all that after ſhould live Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly; oh! what ſhall be the End of thoſe that tread under foot the Son of God, and count the Blood of the Covenant an Unholy Thing and do deſpight to the Spirit of Grace, and daily crucifie the Son of God afreſh, ſpiritually, by their Ungodly Lives, and Ungodly Converſations: For as Sin was the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of the Law, ſo whoſoever ſinneth, rebels againſt God and Chriſt, and doth do deſpight to the Spirit of Grace; and as he that deſpiſed the Law that came by <hi>Moſes</hi> dyed without Mercy, ſo God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved a greater Puniſhment for him that ſins wilfully, and turns not at God's Reproof, but rebels againſt his Spirit, ſets at nought his Counſel, and deſpiſes his Reproof, and hates Knowledge, and doth not chuſe the Fear of the Lord, nor that Light and Grace that inwardly ſtrives with men to turn them from Sin, by inwardly checking and reproving them for ſin in their Hearts and Conſciences, and inward Parts, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels them in their inward Parts to live ſoberly, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly and godly in this preſent World; ſuch, I ſay, muſt inherit everlaſting Flames, and have their Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Lake that burns, where ſhall be <hi>weeping, and wailing, and Gnaſhing of Teeth,</hi> and that for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:36615:12"/>
            <p>And let it be obſerved how God loved the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and preſerved them in all Ages, who feared God, and ſtood in his Counſel, and loved God above all, who feared God becauſe they loved him, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not, but ſtood in Awe; oh, how attentive was God's Ear to hear them! and how did God open their Hearts to intercede for the Ungodly, for their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, for them that hated them without a Cauſe, and grudged them their natural Lives that God had given them! Oh, how was the Lord intreated by them! inſomuch that the Wicked ſpeeded the better for the Righteous; for in the Overthrow of <hi>Sodom,</hi> if there could have been <hi>Ten Righteous</hi> found, God would have ſpared the whole City for the ſakes of <hi>Ten Righteous Perſons:</hi> and <hi>Zoar</hi> was ſpared for <hi>Lot</hi>'s ſake, that Juſt Man.</p>
            <p>It is good and bleſſed for all to be Righteous; for <hi>without Righteouſneſs and Holineſs none ſhall ſee God;</hi> and without ſeeing of God, there is no enjoying that Kingdom which is not of this World, wherein there is Joy and Peace forever. Now there is no man of himſelf can come to be righteous and pure in Heart, but Chriſt muſt cleanſe and purge the Heart, and waſh it by the inward Waſhing of Regeneration, <hi>by ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Heart from an Evil Conſcience by his own Blood;</hi> and the Heart being thus made pure, the Saying of Chriſt in the fifth of <hi>Matthew</hi> comes to be fulfilled to all ſuch, viz. <hi>Bleſſed is the pure in Heart, for they ſhall ſee God.</hi> And in order to bring to this Bleſſedneſs, God hath laid Help upon one that is mighty to ſave, to take off the Burthen of Sin from the Soul, and to give Reſt to the Soul that is weary. Now moſt people will confeſs to this, becauſe it is Scripture;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36615:12"/>but it is one thing to confeſs to it, and another thing to know it experimentally, and to come truly to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>It may be an Objection may be in ſome concerning the <hi>Manner of Coming to Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Unto this I <hi>Anſwer;</hi> The Manner of coming to Chriſt, is to come to his Light and Grace in the Heart, and ſo to be made new Creatures; man muſt leave Sin, and come to a godly Sorrow, which worketh a true Repentance never to be repented of, to come to know Sin to be a Burden, and to feel the weight of it upon the Soul, if he will come aright to Chriſt; for theſe be they that Chriſt called to come to him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Come to me all you that are weary and heavy laden, and I will give you Reſt, I will eaſe you,</hi> Matt. 11.28. And as thou comeſt to him, he will make thee righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and pure in Heart, that thou mayeſt ſee God, and be bleſſed.</p>
            <p>This is that a man cannot do for himſelf, nor no man for him, but Chriſt only: So it is thoſe that mourn and groan under the Burden of Sin, that are fit to come to Chriſt; not them that take Pleaſure in Sin, nor them that love Sin, and plead they muſt live in it term of Life, that is, till they Dye. But them that travail, as <hi>Paul</hi> did, <hi>to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from the Body of Sin, &amp;c.</hi> (Rom. 7.24.) this is the Way to become New Creatures; and theſe be they that hear the Voice of the Son of God and live, as he ſaid, <hi>My Sheep hear my Voice, and the Voice of a Stranger they will not hear,</hi> John 10.27.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36615:13"/>(theſe were good Sheep.) Now to come to hear Chriſt's Voice, is to obey his Spirit, that ſtriveth in the Heart to reclaim the Wicked; and the <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Obedient ſhall dwell in the Land</hi> (in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God) <hi>and ſhall eat of the Good of the Land,</hi> the Bread of Life, and their Souls ſhall partake of the Honey and the Milk that floweth therein, <hi>Iſaeah</hi> 1.19.</p>
            <p>Some may ſay, <hi>If I had been in the dayes of his Fleſh, I would have heard him, and have come to him; but he is aſoended up on high, and ſitteth at the Right Hand of God; and how can I hear him now?</hi> Well it is true, he is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended into Heaven, and is with the Father; But mark this, he is not confined to one place, but as thou mayſt read in the Scriptures,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.5.</note> 
               <hi>He is God over all bleſſed forever; and his Preſence filleth Heaven and Earth;</hi> he is every where, and there is a meaſure or manifeſtation of his Light and good Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit given to thee,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.7.</note> and to every man and woman upon the Earth, that thou and they may profit by it, upon the count of Salvation, and the knowledge of this is made known in thee, or that which may be known of God is manifeſt in thee: and the Scripture ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>The Word is near, even in the Heart and in the Mouth,</hi> &amp;c. there thou mayſt hear it, and as thou obeyeſt the Voice of it, it will give thee Power to do that which it doth require of thee, and by doing this it is that thou mayſt hear his Voice, by keeping to that of God in thee, and thy mind exerciſed in it.</p>
            <p>Here the Voice of the Spirit of Chriſt is known as well as in days paſt, and in Generations gone. So let
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36615:13"/>none deceive themſelves, for the Spirit of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is near to all, whether they will hear him or not; and true it is, that they muſt one day give an account to him whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will or no: therfore let none <hi>deceive</hi> you with lying Vanities or unprofitable Words; for this is he <hi>that ſearcheth the Heart, and tryeth the Reins, and ſheweth unto man what his Thoughts are, the Lord of Hoſts is his Name: and he is not far from any:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 17.27, 28.</note> ſo that no man need ſay, <hi>Who ſhall aſcend to fetch Chriſt? or who ſhall deſcend to fetch Chriſt up? or who ſhall go beyond the Sea?</hi> For ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>The Word of Faith which we Preach is nigh</hi> (but how nigh?) <hi>in the Heart;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.6, 7, 8.</note> and that Chriſt was that <hi>Word of Faith</hi> which <hi>they preacht;</hi> (and ſo we ſay) that People may hear it and do it: And Chriſt ſaid to <hi>John</hi> as may be read in the third Chapter of the <hi>Revelations, Behold I ſtand at the Door and knock, if any man hear my Voice and open the Door, I will come in to him, and ſup with him, and he with me,</hi> Rev. 3.20. It is at the Door of the Heart the Lord knocketh; and they that hear &amp; obey the Spirit of Jeſus, that there knocketh, ſuch come to be born of the Spirit, and by this come to ſup with the Lord, which is not an outward Supper, but an inward en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of ſpiritual Food, <hi>the Bread of Life, that which came down from Heaven,</hi> which Chriſt ſaid, <hi>He that eateth thereof ſhould never dye</hi> (ſhould live for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever) <hi>John</hi> 6.33, 34, 35, 50, 52, 53, 63. and that Bread that a man eating of it never dyes, Chriſt ſaid, <hi>was the true Bread,</hi> that his Father gave from Heaven (then the Prieſts did not give it.) And when the People murmured becauſe Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Except ye eat the Fleſh
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36615:14"/>of the Son of Man, and drink his Blood, ye have no Life in you;</hi> did not Chriſt for their further ſatisfaction make them this Anſwer? <hi>The Words that I ſpeak unto you, they are Spirit, and they are Life; it is the Spirit that quickeneth, the Fleſh profitteth nothing.</hi> Now they that can believe Chriſt, let them, who ſaid, <hi>The Fleſh profitteth nothing,</hi> but the <hi>quickening Spirit</hi> and Power of God, that raiſeth the Soul from Death to Life.</p>
            <p>And this is that we labour to bring People to, that all might come to know that they have a part in him who ſaid, <hi>I am the Reſurrection and the Life,</hi> John 5.25. and ſo to feed at the Table of the Lord, that they may never hunger more.</p>
            <p>And for this we have been and yet are hated of the World, both of Profeſſors and Prophane, but more eſpecially of ſome angry and envious Profeſſors; and no marvel, for none hated Chriſt and the Apoſtles more than they that made Profeſſion of Religion (in thoſe dayes) who were themſelves out of the Life of Righteouſneſs, and in Hatred, Strife and Envy, as too many Profeſſors are now adayes, who ſtick in the outward Obſervations and Ceremonies; one cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Lo, here is Chriſt;</hi> and another, <hi>Lo, there he is;</hi> and all in their own Inventions, or in the Inventions of their Fore-Fathers, or at leaſt in the Imitation of Elementary Things, often Perſecuting and Deſtroying one another about Opinions.</p>
            <p>And theſe are they that are led by a falſe ſpirit; for all people are led by the true or falſe Spirit; for there is but two, the Good and the Bad, which all People upon the Earth are led by; that is, the Spirit
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36615:14"/>of God, or the Spirit of the Devil; and to which of theſe a man gives his Mind to ſerve, <hi>his Servant he is,</hi> and his Converſation is managed by that Spirit, and it may be that both lead to profeſs Religion: for even the Devil in ſome ſenſe is not againſt Peoples making a Profeſſion of Religion; but he makes them ſo blindly Zealous, that they ſhall Hate, Perſecuto or Murder thoſe that will not believe what they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and worſhip as they worſhip, and be of their Religion: The Devil cares not how much People talk of God and Chriſt and Religion, provided they do not deny him to lead them, and ſo become New Creatures; <hi>For they that are not led by the Spirit of Chriſt, are none of his,</hi> Rom. 8.9. And to be led by the Spirit of Chriſt, is to become a New Creature; for all have been in the old Nature <hi>Children of Wrath</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.3.) <hi>we as well as others; till we come to put off the Old Man with his Deeds, and to put on the New Man, which is created after the Image of him that created him, in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs,</hi> (Epheſ. 4.24.) the image of Chriſt, who ſaid, <hi>Behold I make all things New.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And herein cometh the New Birth to be known, by which People come to be Heirs to God's Kingdom, which none ever come to, but they that are born again, which is to live a Life anſwerable to the Truth; and to put off the old Man's Deeds is to put off Sin, for all Sin and Wickedneſs is of the Devil, the old Man, and this is the old Nature by which People are Children of Wrath; and it is the old Leaven the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle commanded to be purged out, that in the room thereof Righteouſneſs may dwell, which is of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36615:15"/>New Nature, and they that come to this in all things, become New Men, and have New Thoughts, New Words and New Works, being begotten and born again by the Spirit of God, all things become New, and all Old Things be done away, to wit, Swearing, Curſing, Lying, Quarreling, Fighting, Stealing, Whoreing, Drunkenneſs, Pride, Envy, Murther, Cozening, Cheating, Covetouſneſs and Idolatry, Diſſimulation and Hypocriſie, all that is Old; and all Falſe Religions muſt be roled together, as a Scrole,<note place="margin">John 4.</note> and a New Worſhip muſt be known, even in Spirit and Truth. And this was that which <hi>John</hi> was ſhewed in the time of his Baniſhment, by him that ſaid to him; <hi>Behold, I create all things New</hi> [Mark the end of the Old] <hi>John</hi> ſaid, <hi>He ſaw a New Heaven and a New Earth, in which dwelt Righteouſneſs, and there was no Sea; but the Old Heaven was roled together as a Scrole, with a great Noiſe, and the Earth was burnt up with every green Tree; and every Iſland and every Bonds-man and every Free-man fled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; and the Elements were melted with fervent Heat:</hi> But theſe things are a Myſtery hid from the Wiſdom of this World; for the Treaſures of Wiſdom and Knowledge are hid in Chriſt Jeſus, who only and alone opens and reveals the Myſteries and ſecrets of God's Kingdom, and alſo of the Devil's Kingdom, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this Revelation of Jeſus none can know the Right way from the Wrong, nor the True Worſhip from the Falſe, becauſe it is ſpiritually diſcerned.</p>
            <p>They therefore that are not led and guided by the Spirit of God, cannot know theſe things; for the true Knowledge &amp; the right Underſtanding of it is fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36615:15"/>to them; therefore they are putting Light for Darkneſs, and Darkneſs for Light; and calling Good Evil, and Evil Good; and the Wrong Way the Right, and the Right Way the Wrong: And in this Blindfold Condition are all the Worſhippers in the World, that are not led by the Spirit of God to Worſhip God in Spirit and in Truth; for there is no Worſhip accepted of God but that which People are led into by the Spirit of God; and for want of keeping to the Spirit of Truth, that leads into all Truth, which in the Heart and Conſcience Reproves for Sin, and Juſtifies men in doing of Good, People run into all manner of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, as well in Judgment, Diſcipline and Worſhip, as in the other things; for though there be a Spirit in man, <hi>Yet it is the Inſpiration of the Almighty that gives a man Underſtanding</hi> how to Worſhip God, and of the Way to Heaven, and what to believe, and what not to believe; and what to do, and what to leave undone; and what will pleaſe God, and what will not pleaſe him.</p>
            <p>But that there is ſuch an immediate Inſpiration, whereby God doth teach and reveal his Mind to his Children in this Age, is oppoſed, vilified and denyed by the Generality; and no marvel, for needs muſt it be ſo, while they are beſide the Truth, and will not come to the Spirit of Truth, to be led by it, but op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it that ſhould lead into all Truth, and give a man to underſtand that which no man can un derſtand by the Wiſdom of this World;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. <hi>ch.</hi> 2.14.</note> for the Scripture ſaith, <hi>The World by Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom knew not God:</hi> but as People come to be made wiſe by God, ſo they come to have an Experience of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:36615:16"/>theſe fore mentioned things: to know the old Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to be diſſolved, and the Elements melted with fervent heat; this is not an outward thing, but an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Work of God; and it was never done by any Power, but the Power of God: And bleſſed be the Name of the Lord, he hath begun this Work in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which is to the Salvation of them that are faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and uſe victoriouſly the ſpiritual Weapons of their Warfare in Righteouſneſs, againſt Sin and Wickedneſs in the Heart; and as they of old ſaid, ſo can many ſay now adayes, <hi>The Weapons of our War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare are not Carnal, but Spiritual, and mighty through God, for the pulling down the Strong Holds of Satan</hi> in man, <hi>Principalities and Powers of Darkneſs; and for the bringing into the Obedience to Chriſt</hi> our Evil Thoughts (2 Cor. 10.4.) that in the room of Sin Everlaſting Righteouſneſs may reign; then that Peace will be known which paſſeth all Underſtandings of this World.</p>
            <p>And as People give way to the Spirit of God, it wars againſt the Devil, and againſt his ſtrong Holds, which is Sin in the Heart; for that is the chiefeſt Place in Man, the <hi>Heart,</hi> therefore God expecteth the Heart: And the Wiſe Man ſaid, <hi>My Son, give me thy Heart,</hi> Prov. 23.26.</p>
            <p>So when Chriſt cometh to rule in the Heart, then all things become new, the Old Nature by him co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be purged out, and a New Nature cometh to be known, which is of the Nature of Chriſt; and here Man comes to be born again, by putting off the Old World's Worſhips, Delights and Pleaſures, which are the old Heaven and Earth in the Heart;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36615:16"/>for Heaven is as Falſe Worſhip, ſo Pleaſures, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, &amp;c. for whatſoever a man ſets his Heart, Mind and Affections upon, more than upon Chriſt, that he makes his Heaven and his God too; ſome made their Bellies their God, and ſome make Covetouſneſs their Heaven, and ſome make Pride their Heaven, whoſe chiefeſt Delight is to deck their Bodies up in fooliſh Toyes, and cannot tell what New Thing many times to invent to put on, or ſpend their Money up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Little do ſuch remember what the Prophet cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Iſa. 40.6. <hi>All Fleſh is but as Graſs, and the Beauty of it but as the Flower of the Field, the Graſs withereth, and the Flower fadeth away</hi> (in like manner doth the Bodies of Men and Women, with the Beauty thereof) <hi>but the Word of the Lord endureth for evermore:</hi> but this holy Word is little minded, little loved or regarded by many, although it ſtrive with People in them, to ſave them from the Wrath to come, and will be with them forever, a Joy to thoſe that are faithful to it, and a torment to the Wicked.</p>
            <p>But the God of this World hath blinded the Eyes of many, and they are willing to be blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him, alwayes delighting themſelves in the things of this Life, till Death ſeizeth upon them; and then their Delights here become their Burden; then they begin to cry out, <hi>Lord, Lord!</hi> but what doth the Scripture ſay of ſuch? <hi>Matt.</hi> 7.21, 22. [mark] <hi>Not every one that ſaith,</hi> Lord, Lord! <hi>ſhall enter the Kingdom of God; but he that doth the will of God:</hi> and the Will of God is, that people <hi>ſhould ceaſe to do Evil, and learn to do well</hi> (Iſa. 1.16, 17.) and cleanſe their Hands and their Hearts, by putting away the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36615:17"/>Evil of their Doings, whilſt they are on this ſide the Grave: For the Scripture ſaith, <hi>There is no Unclean Thing ſhall enter the Kingdom of God;</hi> and all Sin and Wickedneſs is unclean in the Sight of God; and this was that which <hi>John</hi> ſaw was done away, which he called the <hi>Old Heaven</hi> and the <hi>Old Earth;</hi> and ſaid, <hi>He ſaw a New Heaven and a New Earth, wherein dwelleth Righteouſneſs:</hi> which was a real Change in Man and Woman, out of Sin and Wickedneſs, into Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; and ſo Chriſt comes to rule where the Devil ruled; and this is being born again; and without co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to this, none can come to be ſaved, nor go to Heaven.</p>
            <p>Therefore 'tis good for all to conſider this, while there is time to do it, before the Night come, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no man can work for God: for there are many things that hinder man from being born again, as I was about to ſay concerning them that make Viſible Things their Heaven and their God, as ſome make <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Pride</hi> their Heaven and their God; and otherſome <hi>Drunkenneſs, Swearing</hi> and <hi>Lying</hi> their Delight, ſo it is their Heaven and their God; ſome in <hi>Envy, Malice, Hatred</hi> and <hi>Strife, Backbiting</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge;</hi> others delight in <hi>Quarrelling, Fighting</hi> and <hi>Murdering</hi> about Religion; others in <hi>Hunting, Hawk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>Horſe-Racing,</hi> in <hi>Cards</hi> and <hi>Dice,</hi> in <hi>Fooliſh Jeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> ſpending their precious time in <hi>Idle Stories,</hi> which corrupt Youth, and are a Shame to Old Age. Theſe things and many more, while people live in them, they are not born again, nor led by the Spirit of God; for all theſe things are brought forth in people <hi>by the Prince of the Power of the Air, the Spirit
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:36615:17"/>which ruleth in the Hearts of the Children of Diſobedience'</hi> Epheſ. 2.2. But the worſt is, that all theſe things' or moſt of them, are brought forth by ſuch and in ſuch as do pretend to worſhip and Religion; but all ſuch Worſhippers are out of the Fear of God.</p>
            <p>God made Man Upright, but he falling from that Upright State, he came to invent many Wayes to find out that again which he by Diſobedience had loſt; but none could find it, till they came to be led to it by the Spirit of God, the Spirit of Truth, which leadeth and guideth into all Truth; and none come to be led by the Spirit of Truth till they deny themſelves, and take up a Croſs to their own Wills, a Croſs to their old Heaven and to their old Earth, which they have lived and delighted in; not a Croſs of <hi>Wood</hi> or <hi>Stone,</hi> and ſuch outward things as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſet up, but to the Perverſe Nature, and the Selfiſh Will, that the Will of God may be done in Earth as it is in Heaven, in thy Earthen Veſſel; but while the old Heaven, and the old Earth, and the old Beggarly Elements are ſtanding, theſe things cannot be till all that cometh to be done away by the Spirit and Power of God; for by him all things are to be made new in Man and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. For when thy Delight cometh to be ſet on the Law of the Lord, and thy Mind to be ſet on God and Godlineſs above all other things, and to make it thy chiefeſt Joy to ſerve and worſhip God in the Spirit and in the Truth, and to ſeek after a Righteous Life here, thou wilt come to know that New Heaven which <hi>John</hi> ſpoke of in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> wherein dwelleth Righteouſneſs, ſo new Pleaſures and Joyes; for while the Old Nature in thee bears rule, &amp; the old Pleaſures
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:36615:18"/>of Sin yet ſtand in thy Mind and Heart, in that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth Unrighteouſneſs, and that muſt be deſtroyed; and when theſe things by Chriſt come to be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then thou wilt come to know Sanctification, and to be redeemed from Sin by the Spirit of God, and to be ſanctified (as the Scripture ſaith) throughout in Body, Soul and Spirit, and ſo come to know all things to become new, to be changed by the Lord; and this is the New Birth, which is begotten and brought forth by God, which is not of this World, but co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be changed by the <hi>little Leaven, which was hid in the three Meaſures of Meal,</hi> Matth. 13.33. and bleſſed be the Name of the Lord, this little Leaven hath in many brought the three Meaſures into one Lump, and hath changed Body, Soul and Spirit into its own Nature; and in ſuch all things are become new; for the Kingdom of Heaven and the Spirit of it is compared to a <hi>little Leaven,</hi> that was hid in three Meaſures of Meal; for the Spirit of God ſeemeth to moſt people to be of little and of low Eſteem in their Eyes; and the Appearance of his Spirit in them againſt Sin is more hated than any man's; and he is (as the Prophet ſaid, <hi>Amos</hi> 2.13.) <hi>preſt down as a Cart that is laden with Sheaves.</hi> It is Sin and Wickedneſs that the Spirit of God is preſſed down with in the Hearts and Conſciences of People; but Wo be to them one day, if by Faith and Repentance they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move not theſe Weights and Burdens from the Lord's Spirit; this is that which will ſink them down to the Pit of Hell, where there is never any more coming out, its without End, 'tis Torment forever.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is good for all People to be faithful to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:36615:18"/>the Spirit of Chriſt; it is no leſs than the <hi>Power of God to Salvation</hi> in them that are faithful to it; and by this People come to eſcape the Damnation of Hell, and by no other means can ever any eſcape, but as they come to know Chriſt's Spirit to rule in the Heart and Mind over all Impurity; for he is come to bear ſway in the Heart; and therefore <hi>Wiſdom</hi> ſaith, <hi>My Son, give me thy Heart:</hi> and if he rule in the Heart, then that which abounds out of the Heart will be from the Good Motions of Chriſt's Spirit: and as the Holy Man of God ſaid in dayes paſt (<hi>Acts</hi> 17.28.) <hi>In Him we live, and in Him we move, and have our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> this will alſo be witneſſed by them in this day, that know Chriſt to rule in them; for ſuch come to live in him, and to move by him, and in him to have their being: he that came to this ſtate ſaid, (<hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20., <hi>The Life that I now live is by the Faith of the Son of God.</hi> This was a Life out of Sin, in the New Birth, being choſen out of this World, and come to walk in a new and living Way, which leadeth to the Reſt which never will have End: Chriſt is the Leader of ſuch, and they are no more their own, but his; as he is their Leader, ſo he is their Father, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Keeper; when Temptation comes, he is a ſtrong Tower; he is alſo in the Righteous as a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finer's Fire, and as a Fuller with Soap, and as a Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier of Silver; he makes them more pure than Gold, than the Golden Wedge of <hi>Ofer:</hi> he is in all thoſe that are led by him as a Conſuming Fire againſt Sin and all Deceit; and therefore it is ſaid, <hi>Who can dwell with Everlaſting Burnings?</hi> (Iſa. 33.14.) for by that Heat cometh all the <hi>Falſe Worſhips</hi> (which are but Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary)
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:36615:19"/>to be melted with fervent heat; the Zeal of God is kindled againſt them, and the old Earth by this cometh to be burnt up; then co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the New Earth, which <hi>John</hi> ſaw, <hi>wherein dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth Righteouſneſs;</hi> and in ſuch there is known no more Sea; for all people being from the Spirit of Truth, are in their Minds as unſtable as the Waters of the Sea, toſſed to and fro with every Wind of Doctrine, and with every Tempeſt of the Enemy, before they come to be ſetled by the Power of God; but this ſtability being once known, then people come to know a Stay to their Minds, and come (as the Scripture ſaith, Iſa. 26.3. Phil. 4.7.) <hi>to be kept in perfect Peace, and to know that Peace which paſſeth the Underſtanding of this World,</hi> which the Wiſdom of this World compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth not; for they whoſe Minds are thus preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, the Wicked One toucheth them not (1 <hi>John</hi> 5.18.) although he may come with many Snares and Temptations to inſnare and draw aſide, yet while people are kept by the Spirit of God, they are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from them all; for it is no Sin to be tempted, but to enter into the Temptation, that is ſin, then People come to break their Peace with God; when the Devil tempts them to do any Wickedneſs, and they give way to it, this is <hi>making ſhipwrack of Faith and a Good Conſcience,</hi> as by ſad Experience ſome have done; ſee the 1ſt Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> the 1ſt Chapter and the 19th Verſe.</p>
            <p>But the way to prevent this, is to give way to Chriſt, that he may bear Rule in thy Heart and Mind, and that he may order thy Affections and Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and bear ſway in thee, then thou wilt come to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:36615:19"/>know m that ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 14.17.</note> 
               <hi>He that is with you ſhall be in you.</hi> And they that he ſpoke to knew his words fulfilled, and ſo ſpoke by experience that which they were Eye-witneſſes of, and ſaid, that <hi>he wrought all their Works in them and for them:</hi> And I hope there is none that are ſo miſ-led in their Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, as to ſay that Work was Sin, but altogether to <hi>work out Sin;</hi> for that is the <hi>Work</hi> which Chriſt came to do, <hi>To put an end to Sin in People,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24.</note> 
               <hi>and to finiſh Tranſgreſſion in People, and in the room of Sin to bring in Everlaſting Righteouſneſs in People;</hi> for Sin is in <hi>People,</hi> for there is none in the <hi>Beaſts</hi> of the Field but in mankind; for the Beaſts of the Field keep their places, as God created them, and do no way diſpleaſe God, but mankind knows not his Owner, as the poor Ox and Aſs doth, as the Prophet ſaid, <hi>The Ox knows his Owner, and the Aſs his Maſters Crib, but the People know not the Lord,</hi> Iſa. 1.3.</p>
            <p>In the old Nature no Man nor Woman ever knew God, but as they came to be changed and Born again, and ſo to put on the New Man Chriſt Jeſus; the Old man being put off with his Deeds, which is Sin, then Chriſt is known as he ſaid, <hi>Lo,</hi> ſaid he,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> ch. 6. ver. 16.</note> 
               <hi>I will dwell in man, and walk in man; I will be their God, and they ſhall be my People.</hi> To know this is Eternal Life; but God dwelleth not in Sinners, but in them that are pure in Heart; for 'tis the pure in Heart that ſee God, and ſo come to be acquainted with God; here all People that are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with God by this acquaintance, come to know how its with them as to their inward condition, and how it ſtands with their inward man in the ſight
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:36615:20"/>of God, and by the guiding of Gods Spirit all things in man and woman are kept in good order, and by this come to have Power over Sin, and in ſuch there is no need to cry out for want of Power; for God gives Power to them that come to him by Jeſus Chriſt, who hath all Power in Heaven and in Earth in his Hand, and God's love is Univerſal to all People, and deſires not the Deſtruction of any, but rather they would turn from their Wickedneſs and live: Here you may ſee according to the Scripture of Truth, that it is Sin and Wickedneſs that is the cauſe of Death to the Soul; for you may read in the holy Scriptures, that God hath promiſed, that whoſoever will turn from their Wickedneſs, and from their Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations which they had committed, and come to him, In quity ſhall not be their Ruin, ſuch ſhall not Periſh, but have Life Everlaſting; theſe are terms of Salvation that God hath promiſed the Kingdom of Heaven upon, that People may lay down their Heads in Peace, when they are to go hence never to be ſeen more in this World: And man muſt know Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs done away in this Life, <hi>For as the Tree falleth to the North or to the South, ſo it lieth; and as Death lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth People, ſo Judgment will find them, and there is no Repentance in the Grave;</hi> nor calling the time once ſpent back again, nor no Remiſſion of Sin after this Life; <hi>For no unclean thing ſhall enter the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God.</hi> And all Sin is Unclean in the ſight of God, and this is that which Chriſt is come to deſtroy, that People may be Heirs to a Kingdom which is not of this World.</p>
            <p>And this <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſed, when he ſaid, <hi>He had
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:36615:20"/>fought a good Fight, he had finiſhed his Courſe, and had kept the Faith, and henceforth there was laid up for him a Crown of Glory; and not for him only, but for all them that feared God and loved his Appearance,</hi> 2 Tim. 7.8. And this appearance was and is againſt Sin in the Heart; and <hi>Paul</hi>'s fighting was againſt Sin and Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs with Spiritual Weapons, which was the Law of the Spirit of Life in Chriſt Jeſus, which was not with Carnal weapons, but Spiritual, and mighty through God to the pulling down of the ſtrong Holds of Sin: and this was not known only by <hi>Paul,</hi> and of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, but by the Righteous in all Ages, and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Abel,</hi> and <hi>Enoch,</hi> and all the Righteous all along to this day, they that were made Righteous, it was by that Power by which the Apoſtles witneſſed Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, which was the Power and Spirit of God, and this is near to all, that all may be led by it.</p>
            <p>But ſome have ſaid, that <hi>It is not now as it was in the Apoſtles dayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why is it not now as it was in the Apoſtles dayes? what is changed that it is not now as it was then?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O,</hi> ſay they, <hi>we cannot do as they did, and have Power as they had to live and to ſtand againſt Sin, and to come to that Perfect State as they did.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I <hi>Query</hi> thus; What was it that made them Righteous, or gave them Power over Sin and Death? And by what did they War againſt Sin? was it not God that gave them Power over Sin and delivered them from the Evil of this World? and what was it by which they did this, if not by the Spiritual Law of God that is written in the Heart? and if ſo, then whether the Lords Power. Law and Spirit be not the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:36615:21"/>ſame as it was? and whether the Lords Love be not as it was? and whether he hath not the ſame Power to help man as he had? I hope all this will be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and that it was only and alone by the Power and Spirit of God they came to be Righteous, and to witneſs an Overcoming of Sin, and by no Self righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, nor by any other Power, and that the Lord's Law, Power and Spirit is the ſame as it was, and his Love the ſame as it was, and that God has the ſame Power to help men as he had.</p>
            <p>And if this be granted, that it is ſo, then it ſeems the Fault is not in God, <hi>that it is not now as it was in the Apoſtles dayes;</hi> and if the Fault be not in God, then it is in Man: But 'tis my Belief and Experienced Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that there be ſome that are come to witneſs the ſame Power over Sin as the Apoſtles witneſſed in their day: and I believe that it is with Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that are faithful to God, as it was in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles dayes, as concerning having Power over Sin, and to come to a Perfect State in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>But to them that are wallowing in Sin, as a Sow in the Mire, and to them that are pleading for Sin for term of Life, although they may be got under a high Notion of Religion, and out of the open Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the groſs Abominations which are practiſed in the World, yet notwithſtanding this, while they plead for Sin, and live in Sin, herein they are ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to uphold the Devil's Kingdom, and live in that which Pleaſeth the Devil, and Diſpleaſeth God; for Sin is of the Devil's Kingdom, and they that plead for it (to wit, for <hi>Sin</hi>) are pleading for the Devil's Kingdom; and with ſuch I muſt needs
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:36615:21"/>confeſs it was never with them as with the Apoſtles in their day, and them that followed Chriſt in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles dayes, nor in our dayes; and ſuch there were in the Apoſtles dayes, that would not believe and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt; and they knew no Power over Sin, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they came not to him that gives Power, and ſo came not to be Sons of God, becauſe they did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him that was come to give Power to become the Sons of God, as the Scripture ſaith, which we that are in Scorn called <hi>Quakers</hi> do believe to be a true Declaration of thoſe things that ought to be believed, and have a reverent Eſteem of them; and they ſay, <hi>Chriſt came to his own, but his own received him not; but as many as did receive him, unto them he gave Power to become the Sons of God,</hi> John 1.10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p>Receiving of him is to yield to the Motions of his good Spirit in them, and theſe be they which come to know that God is not changed, nor his Power leſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor his Love abated; but he is the ſame to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind to day as yeſterday, and forever; and as there were ſome in the Apoſtles times, that would not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Doctrine of Chriſt, nor the Apoſtles, ſo now in our dayes there are many Profeſſors and Prophane that will not believe Chriſt nor his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, becauſe his Doctrine is againſt Sin, but they cannot abide it, and are crying out, <hi>No Perfection Here,</hi> neither will they believe, that Chriſt is able to do the Work that the Father ſent him to do; for he came <hi>to put an End to Sin, to finiſh Tranſgreſſion, and to bring in Everlaſting Righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is that which they cannot believe, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally they that are got under a Colour of Religion, as
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:36615:22"/>the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> were; they ever were the worſt againſt Chriſt and the Apoſtles, and ſo they are now adayes. For all Religions and Worſhips are Falſe and Vain, except that which Chriſt ſet up above Sixteen Hundred Years ago, <hi>which is in the Spirit and Truth,</hi> which is the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, and the Power of God to Salvation, made known to Mankind in the Heart and Conſcience, as the Scripture ſaith, Rom. 1.19. <hi>That which may be known of God is manifeſt within, for God hath ſhewed it to man,</hi> that Sin by this may be made known, and Righteouſneſs made known, the Way of Life and the Way of Death made known, that loſt Man may not be to ſeek concerning Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; this hath the Lord done in Mercy for us, that none may miſs of that Kingdom which is not of this World; and if any miſs that, it is becauſe of Sin; and this muſt be known to be taken away in this Life; if it could have been done away after this Life, then Chriſt needed not have come and ſuffered for Sin, as he did; nor the Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt have preſt People ſo much to Perfection, as they did, and to make their Calling and Election ſure in this Life: But this is certain, <hi>If ever people come to be Heirs to God's Kingdom, they muſt come to have Aſſurance of it before they go hence, elſe they will miſs of their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, of having a Reſt with God when this Life will End:</hi> And to know Aſſurance, is to know <hi>Sin de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and Righteouſneſs ſet up in the Heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some may be ready to ſay, <hi>How is this poſſible to be, ſeeing our Mortal Bodies are frail, and full of Infirmities, and Weakneſs doth attend us; and when we have done all, we are Unprofitable Servants?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:36615:22"/>
            <p>It is true, all the Service that Man can do, it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable in the ſight of God, if God lead not unto it; all Worſhip, Service and Duty, that is done, ſet up and offered to the Lord, it being done in Man's Will, this is all unprofitable, and unaccepted of God, it being Man's Will, and not the Will of God; for while People live in Sin, and plead for it, and while the Old Nature is ſtanding, their Preaching, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Baptizing and Breaking of Bread, Singing and Family Duties, it is all vain if Chriſt move not to it and lead into it; the Scripture ſaith, <hi>The Prayers of the Wicked are Abomination to the Lord;</hi> and if their beſt Service be Abomination to the Lord, needs muſt the reſt; for all Sin is Abomination at the beſt; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore while people live in Sin, and plead for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation of it, they muſt needs be Wicked; and herein, I ſay, all is unprofitable as people live in this Condition. But there is a State and Condition which is profitable &amp; perfect, and that <hi>Job</hi> came to, and many more of the People of God in all Ages &amp; Generations, that knew the Spirit of God to lead and guide them into all Truth; this is that Spirit which a <hi>Manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of is given to every Man to profit withal,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.7. and they that came to be led by that Spirit, their Prayers avail much, and their Works are the Works of Righteouſneſs, and this is that which God doth accept of; and I hope there is none that will dare to ſay, <hi>That the works of Chriſt are not perfect,</hi> they that know Chriſt to work all their Works in them and for them, which Works are perfect and profitable in all they that are pure in Heart; and by this Sin cometh to be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and by the Power of God Perfection is known,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:36615:23"/>and not by any thing of man's Righteouſneſs, Service or Invention, which is but Outward Lip Service, which Chriſt complained againſt, concerning them that honoured him with their Mouthes, but their Hearts were far from him; it is now juſt ſo with moſt ſorts of People, Prieſts, Profeſſors and Prophane, that are come no further than the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees</hi> were, and the <hi>Jews</hi> and High Prieſts in Chriſt's dayes, when he in the Body of Fleſh walked upon the Earth, they then were much oppoſing Chriſt and the Apoſtles Doctrine, becauſe they preach't up another Doctrine contrary to the Traditions, who were buſie about Outward Duties and Services, Praying, Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and Singing, and Eating. Drinking, Waſhing, and making a great flouriſh with Outward Worſhip, and boaſting about Religion, which was but in Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, Types, Figures and Shadows, altogether in Outward things, as people are now adayes, that are not come to the Spiritual Worſhip, which is in Chriſt Jeſus; theſe were in Ages paſt, and are in this our Age, all crying out againſt that <hi>inward Principle</hi> which Chriſt and the Apoſtles exhorted People to, as you may read in the Scriptures of Truth how Chriſt ſaid, <hi>He was the true Light, that lighteth every man that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into the world,</hi> John 1.9. This Light ſhineth in the Heart and Conſcience, there to ſhew a man his Thoughts, and to ſet his Inward Condition in view before him, becauſe nothing elſe can do it; and this was that Light that ſhone in <hi>Paul</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>O wretched Man that I am! who ſhall deliver me from the Body of this Death?</hi> Rom. 7.24. It was the Light of Chriſt that ſhewed him his wretched ſtate, and not
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:36615:23"/>only ſo, but gave him Power over it, and he being faithful to it, through great Self-denyal, he taking up the Croſs to his own Will, whereby he was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified to the World, and the World to him, was made able to travail through great Tribulations, Exerciſes and Perſecutions, both by Profeſſors and Prophane, and by his own Country Men; and all this Hatred and Malice was raiſed up in them by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> becauſe he was turned to the Spirit and Light of Chriſt Jeſus in himſelf, and led a new Life, and worſhipped God in another manner than he did before (to wit) <hi>in the Spirit and in the Truth,</hi> he being come to that which was out of their ſight, to things that Chriſt had revealed to him, and by this he prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and turned People from Darkneſs to the Light of Chriſt in themſelves, and from Satan's Power to the Power of God; for this thing was <hi>Paul</hi> enviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſecuted, and cryed-out againſt, and accounted Mad, and ceaſed not their Purſuit till they had mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him at <hi>Rome;</hi> and for this very thing do Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, Prieſts, Magiſtrates, and many others hate us, now adayes, for turning of People from Darkneſs to Light, &amp; from Satan's Power to the Power of the living God &amp; many have been the Inventions, Conſultations, &amp; Contrivances againſt us, both by Parliaments, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, Magiſtrates, Biſhops, Prieſts, Profeſſors and Prophane, that if the Lord had not ſtood by us, we had been deſtroyed long ago; but the Righteous God, that pleads the innocent Cauſe of his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, hath ſo kept us and preſerved us by his Living Power, that our Adverſaries had never ought to prove againſt us, but only the Law of our God, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:36615:24"/>this honeſt <hi>Daniel</hi> was accuſed for, but conſider what became of his Accuſers, and the Accuſers of the Righteous in all Ages, and then read within what will become of the Perſecutors of God's People in this Age, and for the future; and who ever proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered that fought againſt God? for the Hand of God is too ſtrong for the whole World, and it was ever turned upon them that uſed Violence, and Miſery muſt be their Portion, if they Repent not.</p>
            <p>Therefore 'tis good for all people to look home, and to conſider how it is with them, as to their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Condition; for it I am Wrong, thou ſhalt not give an Account for me, nor I for thee, but every one for themſelves; therefore it is good for every one to walk in the Light, while the Light ſhineth, before Darkneſs come upon thee, and there be no more Light, and thou left without Remedy for Salvation; for it is the Light that bringeth Salvation, as you may read in the Scriptures what the Holy Men ſay, 2 Cor. 4.6. That <hi>God who commanded Light to ſhine out of Darkneſs, hath ſhined in our Hearts, to give us the Light of the Knowledge of the Glory of God in the Face of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> that is, in the Appearance of Jeſus Chriſt. Chriſt is the Light, and the Light is Chriſt Within, the Hope of Glory; and this they ſpoke who were Witneſſes of his inward Appearance, of his revealing himſelf in their Hearts and Inward Parts.</p>
            <p>And further, the Scripture ſaith, That <hi>this is the Condemnation, that Light is come into the World, and men loved Darkneſs rather than Light becauſe their Deeds are Evil,</hi> John 3.19.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:36615:24"/>
            <p>This is Salvation to them that are ſaved, and Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to them that are damned (to wit) the Light; for you may ſee, that they that hated the Light were condemned by it, and it was and is hated by all that love and plead for Sin, which is Evil; for while peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple live in Darkneſs, which is Evil, they ſee not the Evil Effect that Darkneſs will produce to them that love it, nor the Miſery that doth attend them, and therefore they hate the Light; for the Light makes Sin appear exceeding ſinful, and dreadful to behold; and they that are not willing to leave their Sins; get up into Diſregard and Hatred againſt the Light that ſheweth them it, and ſheweth to them their States; this is that which troubleth people in their Minds, and diſquietteth them in their inward Parts for following their Luſts and Pleaſures, and therefore hated by them; for this is oftentimes troubling of them for creeping under falſe Colours of Religions, and falſe Security, and lets them have no true Peace under any invented Religion, that is not ſet up by God and Chriſt; and alſo troubleth the common Prieſts for making a Trade of the Scriptures, and Merchandize of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who with their Lyes make People believe all is well with them, when it is no ſuch thing, and ſo cheat People both of their Souls and Money, and all this they do for Money; but People are not willing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this, becauſe it is an eaſie Road, and pleaſing to the Old Nature and old courſe of Life; and here they can live and pleaſe the baſeſt of men, and do accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Traditions and Doctrines of man, although it be never ſo contrary to God; and here the Blind lead the Blind, and think all is well, till Death comes,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:36615:25"/>and then they come to ſee all is in vain, their ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Money for that which is not Bread, and their Labour for that which ſatisfies not the immortal Soul; and then begins to ſay, <hi>O that I had another day! I would not do as I have done;</hi> and the Reaſon of this is, becauſe they have been ſeeking the Living among the Dead, and Life where no Life is; for there is no Life among the Prieſts in their dead Profeſſions, which will ſatisfie any man's hungering immortal Soul, for that which ſatisfies peoples immortal Souls, Prieſts and Profeſſors are crying out againſt, becauſe it trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles them in their Sin and Falſe Worſhips, and for making a Trade of the Scriptures, and Merchandize of the People; and for this they are crying out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it almoſt in every Pulpit, and almoſt in every Profeſſors Meeting, crying and railing againſt the Light of Chriſt, Grace and Truth in the inward parts; one calling it, <hi>A Diabolical Light;</hi> others cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it, <hi>A Natural Light,</hi> and <hi>The Check of a Natural Conſcience;</hi> and ſome in their Ignorance are ſo impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent as in plain <hi>Engliſh</hi> to call the Light of Chriſt, <hi>A Deviliſh Light;</hi> and ſome call it, <hi>The Quakers Light,</hi> and <hi>An Inſufficient Light,</hi> with many other Reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Villifying Terms againſt Chriſt and the Light, not only in their Pulpits, but alſo in their Lives and Practices at other times; for they find, that when people once come to walk in the Light of Chriſt, and to be led by the Spirit of God they will have no more of their blind Teaching, then down goes their Trade and their great Gain of Merchandize, with all their Gifts and Rewards, and <hi>Babylon</hi> with all her Bravery, and the old Whore, which ſate upon
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:36615:25"/>the Waters, and made many People drunk with the Cup of her Fornication. When once People come to be led by the Spirit of Jeſus, which is revealed in mankind (to wit) the Spirit of Truth, which lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into all Truth, and guideth into all Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; Then down falleth all <hi>Babylons</hi> Merchants, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Hell, and altogether, and then cometh Chriſts Kingdom to be ſet up and known, which is hid from the Wiſdom of this World.</p>
            <p>But ſome may ſay. <hi>Revelation and Inſpiration is now ceaſed; and how ſhall People come to that State thou ſpeakeſt of now adayes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I <hi>Anſwer,</hi> If <hi>Revelation</hi> be ceaſed, then Salvation and the Knowledge of God is ceaſed; and if this be true, then what have Prieſts to Preach now adayes? for Chriſt ſaid, <hi>No man knows the Father but the Son, and him to whom the Son will reveal him</hi> (Mat. 11.27.) and that none came to him but by the Father, whom Chriſt the Son revealeth: And <hi>Paul</hi> alſo ſaid, <hi>That when it pleaſed God to reveal his Son in him, he conſulted not with Fleſh and Blood</hi> (but with the Son, whom the Father revealed.) So here its plain to the Eye that ſeeth, which God opened, that <hi>Revelation</hi> is not cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but the Son revealeth the Father, and the Father reveals the Son in People, as witneſſed by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> to ſhow to People their inward conditions, how it ſtands with them in the ſight of God; and this <hi>Paul</hi> did not ſee nor find out with all his Learning, nor with his great Zeal, or great Religion, till Chriſt the Light was revealed in him; neither ſhall any man upon the Earth come to know how it is with him as to his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:36615:26"/>condition, till he come to know Chriſt revealed in him, and to Inſpire him by his holy Spirit, as I have hinted before, that although there be a Spirit in man, yet it is the Inſpiration of the Almighty that gives a man an Underſtanding: and if it be (as ſome ſay) that Inſpiration is ceaſed, then all true Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing concerning Salvation and Spiritual matters is loſt; then what need any go after the Prieſts or any other Profeſſors, if there be no Knowledge of God or Chriſt to be attained to? Away with all their blind and falſe Juggles which they bewitch People with, that they might not obey the <hi>Truth,</hi> it is all <hi>Lyes</hi> &amp; <hi>Deluſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Revelation</hi> or <hi>Inſpiration</hi> is not ceaſed; <hi>Paul</hi> was ſince Chriſt, and he witneſſed Revelation and Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and many more ſince him; and I believe Chriſt and <hi>Paul</hi> ſpoke true, and that the Scripture is true, and all that is againſt it is Deceit; and the Scripture holds forth <hi>Revelation</hi> and <hi>Inſpiration</hi> is not ceaſed; although in the time of the Law the Prieſts Lips were appointed to preſerve the Peoples Knowledge, and the people were appointed to ſeek the Law at their Mouthes: Yet now it is not ſo, but every one that lacks Knowledge is to ask of God, who gives Liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and upbraideth not ſuch as ask in Faith.</p>
            <p>But ſay ſome, <hi>You</hi> Quakers <hi>do not Baptize your Children, nor receive the Sacrament, as we do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I <hi>Anſwer,</hi> If thou meaneſt Sprinkling of Infants, I do not believe that was uſed by any of the People of God in many Ages ſince Chriſt and the Apoſtles dayes, and therefore I do not know why any ſhould uſe it,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:36615:26"/>ſeeing there is not any Preſident in all the Scripture that it was ever uſed by any of the Primitive <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> neither in all the Scripture do I find any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God for it; and therefore why ſhould we uſe it? beſides, I look upon the thing as it is now practiſed, to be a great offence to God in the Actors of it, and for this Reaſon which I ſhall render, for when the Prieſts and People meet together to <hi>Chriſten</hi> or <hi>Baptize</hi> a Child, (as they ſo call it) moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Parents of the Child muſt get ſome other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as they can, to ſtand for the Child, and there they muſt Promiſe and Vow three things in the Child's Name; firſt, <hi>That it ſhall forſake the Devil and all his Works, Pomps and Vanities of this wicked world, all the ſinful Luſts of the Fleſh.</hi> Secondly, <hi>That the Child ſhall believe all the Articles of the</hi> Chriſtian <hi>Faith.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>That it ſhall keep Gods holy Will and Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and walk in the ſame all the dayes of its Life.</hi> This is Confuſion, and contrary to their Faith and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple; for they do not believe that any ſuch thing can be, or ſuch a ſtate attained to: Now to enjoyn People to promiſe that the Child ſhall do that which they themſelves do believe is Unpoſſible, is Folly and Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Coufuſion and a Snare to them, to whom they make ſo to imagine: For if one ſhould ask the Prieſt, or any of them, if they could live ſuch a Life as they Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and Vow the Child ſhall do, they will ſay, <hi>No it cannot be.</hi> And are crying out in almoſt every Pulpit, and almoſt in every Profeſſors Meeting, againſt ſuch a Perfect Life as they promiſe and vow the Child ſhall live, and ſaying, <hi>No Perfection here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For to forſake the <hi>Devil</hi> &amp; all his Works, &amp; to keep
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:36615:27"/>Gods holy Will and Commandments, is <hi>Perfection.</hi> Now conſider the Diſtraction, Confuſion, Madneſs and Blindneſs of this People, this is one of the chief Articles of the Church, to Promiſe and Vow that the Child ſhall forſake the Devil and all his Works, and live ſo all its Life long; this is the firſt thing they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn a Member of their Church, in the receiving a Member into their Church as part of their form of Worſhip, and in their Pulpits Preach againſt it, that is, againſt the principal part of their <hi>Articles</hi> of belief in <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> inaſmuch as they ſay, <hi>there is no Perfection here:</hi> O the Darkneſs &amp; groſs Darkneſs that is over this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the blindneſs and ignorance they are in concerning their Salvation! it is hard to expreſs how they are miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, the <hi>blind Leaders</hi> of the Blind, till many a thouſand fall into the Ditch: But bleſſed be the Name of the <hi>Lord,</hi> who hath drawn me and many more out of it, and hath ſet our Feet upon a Rock, as <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>Out of the Miery Clay.</hi> For all theſe Performances, and their beſt Duties are but as Mire and Clay in the ſight of God, and we that were in it as well as others, hath the <hi>Lord</hi> raiſed up to bear a Living Teſtimony againſt this Idolatrous Worſhip, and falſe Imaginations, that others may come to ſee where they are, and come out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, before they fall together into the Pit of Hell, where there is never coming out more. For the Prieſts and all other Sect-Maſters are blind Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Blind; for do but conſider the manner of their proceeding in this matter of Sprinkling of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and what it doth produce; the Prieſt he ſprinkleth Water in the Face of the Child, and ſaith, <hi>I Baptize thee in the Name of the Father, Son, and holy
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:36615:27"/>Ghoſt.</hi> And that they reckon maketh a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> of the Child, (to wit) a Child of God, a Member of Chriſt, and an Inheritor of the Kingdom of God (an abſolute Deluſion) and then there they muſt have ſome other People, good or bad, to ſtand bound for the Child, and theſe they call <hi>God-Fathers</hi> and <hi>God-Mothers;</hi> as if the God of Heaven and Earth had Fathers and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers made of wicked Men and Women: for do but mind, theſe people take the Work of God upon them, inaſmuch as they take upon them to Promiſe and Vow that the <hi>Child ſhall forſake the Devil and all his Works,</hi> which is to live without Sin, and no leſs then all the dayes of his Life, which is a thing all the World can never do; for inaſmuch as they promiſe that the Child ſhall forſake the Devil and all his Works, this doth include all Sin whatſoever; for there is no Sin, nor never was, but is of the Devils work, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they take that upon them which none can do but God and Chriſt: and therefore <hi>Chriſt is come to deſtroy Sin, to put an End to Sin, to finiſh Tranſgreſſion, and to bring in Everlaſting Righteouſneſs;</hi> for all man's Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs is but as filthy Rags, and when he hath done all that he can, while he is in the old Nature, it is all unprofitable.</p>
            <p>And further conſider both Prieſts and People, how the Prieſts Err in compelling people to do that in this caſe which they are ignorant of, and cannot give An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for what they do; and here the Blind are Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Blind: For neither Prieſts nor People know in this matter what they do, for if they did, ſome of them would not do it; for when ſome in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the Lord have asked them, why they did
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:36615:28"/>do theſe things, which there is no Scripture for, they could not well tell what to ſay; ſome have ſaid, <hi>The Law of the Nation is for it;</hi> Others in a blind manner will ſay, <hi>That if they ſhould not do it, their Children would be Damned,</hi> becauſe they think that maketh them <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> when few of them know what a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> is; for a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> is one that walketh like Chriſt, or as Chriſt would have him, and ſo to be United to Chriſt. Some will Anſwer, and ſay, <hi>That it was uſed in our Fore-Fathers dayes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we will uſe it.</hi> It was ſaid, <hi>In the time of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance the Lord winked, but now he hath removed the Clouds of Ignorance, and made theſe things known,</hi> and hath cleared up the underſtandings of a Remnant more in this Age than in ſome Ages paſt, and hath manifeſted the emptineſs, barrenneſs, unfruitfulneſs and unprofitableneſs of the Traditions of the Ignorant, and is calling to Repentance; and the People of this Age have as much need of Repenting of this thing of Sprinkling as any one thing; for in the manner as it is now uſed, and hath been for ſome time paſt, it is very wicked and abominable in the ſight of God: and why may not people as well plead for their Fore-Fathers Drunkenneſs, Swearing, Lying and Whoreing as for this?</p>
            <p>For note this one thing, when they go to make a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> as they ſuppoſe, do but mark them in the Action, when they are met together, they behave themſelves more like People of making <hi>Heathens,</hi> than <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> for it is common for them (they take occaſion at ſuch times) to Feaſt, Play, Dance, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel and be drunk at the time when they practiſe ſuch
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:36615:28"/>things. And this is their manner of making <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> who make uſe of thoſe opportunities of their ſo meeting to commit ſuch Abominations: but I would leave to the ſerious conſideration of any ſober People, whether theſe Actions and Practices be the way to make <hi>Chriſtians?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O! the horrid Abominations and Pollutions that People do commit in this and almoſt in all their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, when they meet together, as they ſay, to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God! the Lord is weary of bearing with it, and his Indignation is againſt them that run into any thing, and call it Service and Duty to God, when God hath not commanded it, nor required it, nor his Spirit led them to do it: Theſe things are an Abomination to the Lord, and Chriſt is come to judge the World of Sin, of Righteouſneſs and of Judgment; for people that are got into any Judgment or Righteouſneſs, as to Religion and Worſhip, which they are not led and guided into by the Spirit of God, although it were a likeneſs of the true Worſhip which the People of God in Ages paſt did do in obedience to the Spirit of God, and where things that were accepted of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done and acted by the holy men of God, as they were moved by his holy Spirit, were well-pleaſing to God in their Day and Time, they being but Shadows and Figures of the Subſtance Chriſt Jeſus, which is come, and hath put an end to them outward things, &amp; now is calling of People to worſhip in the Spirit and in the Truth; for Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Such the Father ſeeketh to worſhip him.</hi> So now though People may run into theſe things, which were good in their Time and Day, as Circumciſion was in its day; ſo were other things
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:36615:29"/>in their day and time, as <hi>John's</hi> Baptiſm, breaking of Bread, and many other things before, as the Paſſover, &amp; the Brazen Serpent which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſet up, was good till it was Idolized; and in the time of the Law there were many things uſed, as Sacrifice, and Burnt Offerings, Sin Offerings and Peace Offerings, the Blood of Bulls and Goats, the Aſhes of a Heifer, with many out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, (but as to the Sprinkling of Children we never read of) which made not the comers thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Perfect, as to the cleanſing of the Conſcience; for that was a Work alwayes done by the Spirit and Power of God; though it pleaſed God to condeſcend to mans low and weak Capacity in theſe outward things, till the fulneſs of time was come, in which he would ſend Chriſt the Subſtance of all thoſe Types and Figures, and Shadowy outward things, and the Subſtance being come (to wit) the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> Chriſt Jeſus; the Shadows end in him, and the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thereof comes to be fulfilled in them that believe and obey the Truth (to wit) the followers of Chriſt Jeſus: and <hi>John</hi> he ſpoke concerning his Commiſſion or Miniſtration, that he was to Decreaſe, but Chriſt was to Increaſe.</p>
            <p>For if you obſerve, <hi>John</hi> was ſent a fore-runner of Chriſt, to prepare the Way of the Lord, and make his Pathes ſtraight, and to Baptize in Water them that did believe the Teſtimony of <hi>John</hi> concerning Chriſt; and this was in order to a further Work which Chriſt would come to do, as <hi>John</hi> ſaid, which was to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize with Fire and with the holy Ghoſt: So them that are come to be baptized with the holy Ghoſt, and with Fire, they are come to the Subſtance Chriſt Jeſus, and to them the Shadows are ended.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:36615:29"/>
            <p>And as for the Word <hi>Sacrament,</hi> there is no ſuch Word in the Scriptures, that I know; but as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſt breaking of Bread with his Diſciples, that was not ſpoken of as in relation for all men to uſe it, but to his Diſciples alone; for he thus ſpoke and ſaid unto them, <hi>As often as ye do this, do it in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of me, and in ſo doing</hi> (ſaid he to them, not to the World) <hi>you ſhew the Lord's Death till he come.</hi> For he had promiſed to them, <hi>He that was with them; ſhould be in them.</hi> So they were to ſtay at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> till they were indued with Power from on High, which was to know his Second Coming, ſpiritually, without Sin, unto Salvation, which accordingly he performed to them; and then there was no need for to do any thing without to bring them to Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of Chriſt, the Hope of Glory, within them; he was then come to guide their Minds and Hearts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Truth.</p>
            <p>So when his Diſciples were endewed with Power from on High, then in Authority they went into all Nations, baptizing them into the Name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son and Holy Ghoſt: He doth not ſay with Outward Water, but <hi>into the Name of the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt:</hi> And the Name of the Lord is a ſtrong Tower, and the Righteous flee to it, and are ſaved from the Devouring Adverſary: we have cauſe to praiſe the Lord for this; for this is known in our dayes, as it was in dayes paſt. But now for People to run into the Imitation of theſe things, and not by Motion from the Lord, becauſe it hath been uſed in times paſt by the People of God; I ſay, for others to run into it, that never came to witneſs a being in
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:36615:30"/>that ſtate which the People of God were in, this is that Worſhip which is built upon the Sand, which when the Storms come, and the Winds of Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion blow, then that Building falls, and great is the Fall of it; and this Righteouſneſs Chriſt is come to judge as well as Sin: So whatſoever is ſet up, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it may be ſeemingly Righteous in the Eyes of People, which they have been ſeeking to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, it muſt all down, as well as their Sins; for it is all alike in the ſight of God; for People have been ſeeking out eaſie Wayes to ſerve God in; for this worſhipping of God in Spirit and Truth they do not like, the Gate that leadeth to it is ſo ſtrait, that they muſt ſo much deny themſelves, that they cannot get in at it with their Body of Sin; and this is ſuch a Croſs to their own Wills, that they that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the Pleaſures of Sin cannot abide to think on it, but get up what they can againſt it, and would fain have an eaſier Way than Chriſt, and reckon him an hard Maſter, becauſe he would have them leave the Pleaſures of Sin, that they may be ſaved in the Day of Account, which will ſuddenly come upon all the World, to give an Account of their Deeds done in the Body, whether they are Good or Evil.</p>
            <p>Therefore 'tis good for all People to ſee that their Deeds are Good, before it be too late, and lay aſide that which hindereth, that they may enter in at the ſtrait Gate, before it be ſhut, never more to be open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for it is God that openeth, and it is him that ſhutteth; and if he ſhut again, all the World ſhall never open more; and though they may then ſeek,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:36615:30"/>they cannot find: and many times when it pleaſes God to open the blind Eye, ſo that they come to ſee, they ſee there is ſo much to deny and to do away, that they are willing to be blind again, and ſo begin to hate that which ſhewed it them, and even them alſo that are obedient to it, for the ſake of him who in Good Will would ſave them from Hell: There are many things that hinder People from entring in at the ſtrait Gate; <hi>for ſtrait is the Gate &amp; narrow is the Way which leads unto eternal Life, &amp; few there be that find it,</hi> becauſe they are ſeeking the Wrong Way; moſt People are ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every one his own Way, and the Way of the Lord is neglected; for in that Way they cannot walk in their old courſe of Life; for I will render many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances why many are ſtriving and cannot enter in at the ſtrait Gate. This is ſtrait to the Carnal Man, but to the Spiritual Man it is eaſie, or it is made eaſie to them by the Spirit of God; but to the Sinner 'tis hard; the Drunkard, becauſe of his Drunkenneſs cannot enter into the Kingdom of God; the Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, becauſe of his Swearing; the Lyar, becauſe of his Lying; the Covetous Man, becauſe of his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs; the Cozening, Deceitful, Envious and Malicious-minded Men cannot enter becauſe of theſe things; the Proud and Lofty, or them that ſpend their time in Playing &amp; Sporting, in Vanity and Jeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, cannot enter; theſe and all ſuch things have and do hinder from coming into the Kingdom of Heaven; the Whoremonger, Thief and Murderer, the Hypocrite or Blaſphemer, cannot enter; and they that be got under a Cover of Religion which is not true, but falſe, cannot enter, though it make a
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:36615:31"/>great ſhew, it being not right, this hindreth many from coming to God, and is one of the greateſt Snares the Devil hath to deceive with among men, and doth in this kind deceive Millions of People; for here he makes them believe <hi>All is well,</hi> and ſo being under a Profeſſion they are willing to believe it; but he cannot ſo eaſily perſwade them that are in open Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs <hi>that it is well with them;</hi> for they have no ſuch Cover for their Sins; and therefore Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Publicans and Harlots ſhould enter the Kingdom before ſuch,</hi> Matth. 21.31.</p>
            <p>And for them that profeſs the Truth, and do not walk in it, they ſhall never enter the Kingdom of God.</p>
            <p>All theſe fore mentioned things, and many more that might be mentioned, do hinder many from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering in at the Strait Gate; theſe be the Weights and Burdens which were and are to be laid aſide, which do eaſily beſet People; and it is not applying of Promiſes (as they call it) will do it, in that Way which Carnal-minded Men do apply them; for there is no Promiſe of coming to the Kingdom of God (which Kingdom is not of this World) but upon ſuch terms of being born again, and ſo becoming new Creatures; and then ſuch come to know the In-ſide cleanſed of Sin by him that hath regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated them, which is the Lord from Heaven, the Second <hi>Adam,</hi> the Quickening Spirit; for 'tis not making clean the Out-ſide will do, and ſtill the In-ſide to be full of Sin; and here many People have been cheated of their Souls, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving of them that have ſmoothed them up in
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:36615:31"/>Sin; for when it hath pleaſed the Lord many times to awaken people out of Sin, that have been aſleep in Sin, and when they are a little awakened, and by that Light which then ſhineth in them come to ſee Sin appear as it is exceeding ſinful, and he that ſhews unto man his Thoughts, he it is that ſets all in order before them, and ſo people come to ſee, that it is not as it ſhould be with them, as concerning their Peace with God; and then not knowing what it is that ſheweth them how it is with them, and that God is ſo near them, neither do they know that that which ſheweth them their Sin, is able to deliver out of it, and to give them Power over it, becauſe it is ſo ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by their Teachers, therefore they ſleight it alſo; and under this Trouble of Mind many a poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is under great Diſtreſs, ſeeing his Sin is remaining and that the Wages thereof is Death, finding no Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per on Earth, but wandering in dry places, ſeeking Reſt, but finding none, becauſe they are ſtill reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Fleſh and Blood, not joyning to that which ſheweth them their Sin; here they are at a Loſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Salvation; and in this State and Condition many are going from one Profeſſion to another, there inquiring of one Teacher or another, <hi>What they muſt do to be eaſed of their Troubled Mind, and come to ſome Satisfaction concerning their poor Souls;</hi> then theſe blind Teachers begin to turn them to Wrong Wayes, herein cometh Deſtruction upon many a poor Soul, being led by the blind Leaders of the Blind into ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Crooked and By Wayes, which lead to Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and here one he bids them apply the Promiſes; another, he cryes out, <hi>Go into the Water;</hi> another
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:36615:32"/>turning them to the <hi>Bread and Wine;</hi> and another to <hi>worſhip Images,</hi> which can neither hear, ſpeak or ſee. So here they are turning People to Outward Things, when the chief cauſe lies within, and cannot be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged out by theſe outward things, but only by the Power of God: Man may make clean the Out-ſide, but the In ſide muſt be cleanſed by God; and if the In-ſide be clean, then the Out-ſide alſo will be clean; the Out-ſide may be clean and painted, and the In-ſide full of Rottenneſs; and in this State and Condition the Dawbers with Untempered Morter dawb over peoples Wounds, but could never cure them: I am not ſpeaking againſt thoſe Outward Means which the Lord calleth any into; but for People to run into any thing which they are not called to, though it may be in Pretence of Service and Worſhip to God, this ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did not will eaſe any of their Burden of Sin, which they groan under, but it is Chriſt alone that muſt do it, it muſt be upon his own Terms, and not as Man would have it; but there are many <hi>Lo Heres,</hi> turning people to Outward Things, and not to Chriſt's Appearance within; one crying, <hi>Lo here is Chriſt,</hi> and another <hi>Lo there he is,</hi> in this or the other Outward Obſervation: But what ſaid Chriſt of ſuch that ſpoke after this manner? <hi>Go not after them</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>that ſhall ſay,</hi> Lo here is Chriſt, <hi>or</hi> Lo there he is, <hi>go not forth, believe them not;</hi> for <hi>that which may be known of God is near,</hi> which is called the Word, which is in the Heart and in the Mouth; and this is that which ſhews unto Man his Sin, and alſo able to take it away; for he is come to put an End to Sin, and to finiſh Tranſgreſſion, ſo to bring in Everlaſting Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs:
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:36615:32"/>this is the Work which he came to do, which all the blind Guides can never do; and this is he which bringeth that Peace and Wiſdom which paſſeth all Underſtandings of Men.</p>
            <p>And further, Chriſt ſaid to the <hi>Jews, The Kingdom of Heaven is within you.</hi> But obſerve, inſtead of turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing People to this inward Principle which Chriſt told People of, the Blind Guides are altogether turning People unto outward things, and ſo here ſetting them to make clean the Out-ſide of the Cup and Platter, and People are cheated of their Souls; for one is cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, The <hi>Maſs-Book</hi> is the Way to come to Heaven, and <hi>Praying to dead Saints,</hi> and <hi>Worſhipping of Images;</hi> others crying, <hi>Dipping</hi> and <hi>Bread and Wine</hi> is the Way; and another crying, The <hi>Church-Faith</hi> is the Way; another ſteps up, and ſaith, His <hi>Directory</hi> is the Way; and there is another ſaying, The <hi>Common Prayer-Book</hi> is the Way; ſo here are many Wayes ſet up by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of Man in the fallen ſtate, ſo leading many Thouſands of poor People into theſe outward things, and not keeping to that or being turned to that which ſearcheth the Heart and tryeth the Reins, and for want of this come to loſe their Souls Reſt and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with God; for 'tis not the making clean the Out-ſide will do, but them that are cleanſed within, theſe are them which God delights in; it is the Pure in Heart that ſee God; here every one cometh to know how it is with them; for God is with the Pure in Heart, and by him people come to know the Way which leadeth to Everlaſting Life; and this is he that we ſay is the Way to come to that Kingdom which is not of this World, where no Mortal Man
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:36615:33"/>ever came to; and the Scripture directeth people to him, and bears Teſtimony of him, which we whom the World in Scorn calls <hi>Quakers</hi> do faithfully believe is true; and though we have been belyed and falſly accuſed in that matter, we deſire the Lord may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them that have been guilty of that thing, in ſaying, we <hi>Deny the Scriptures;</hi> for there are no Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple own the Scriptures more than we do; for 'tis not every one that readeth it that doth own it, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though 'tis good to read it; 'tis they that anſwer and fulfil the Sayings of Scripture in Life and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation that truly own them, and theſe come to know the Myſteries of them, and not every one that can talk of them, as the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> could, and premeditate things in their Brains, and talk of them in their Wills, but 'tis he only that doth the Sayings of them that cometh to know the Comfort and Benefit of them.</p>
            <p>For People are miſtaken in this, thinking that by often reading the Scriptures (little minding what they read) that this will do God Service; No, no, 'tis they that read with Underſtanding, and come to Practiſe the ſame, who come to know all falſe Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips from the true, and the true from the falſe.</p>
            <p>For the Scripture doth not direct people to it ſelf, but to Chriſt Jeſus; for we ſay, he is the Way, the Truth and the Life; and we ſee where Chriſt taketh them off from having ſo much dependency on the Scriptures, and ſaid thus, <hi>Search the Scriptures, for in them you think to have Eternal Life, and they are they which teſtifie of me; but you will not come to me that you may have Life,</hi> John 5.39. So we ſay that Chriſt is
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:36615:33"/>he that giveth Life, and without him no man can come to God. And this is our Principle, and that which we do faithfully believe, and the Scriptures are on our ſide as a Cloud of Witneſſes: And we do not believe that any of theſe outward things will do, as Praying to them that are dead, or Worſhipping of Images, or Signing with a Croſs, or any of theſe things; but man muſt become a new Creature, all old things muſt be done away.</p>
            <p>Neither do we believe that Water, Bread or Wine can do any thing towards cleanſing of the Conſcience; Neither do we believe that the <hi>Church Faith,</hi> (as they call it) nor their <hi>Directory;</hi> but he that ſaid, <hi>Before</hi> Abraham <hi>was I am,</hi> 'tis he that is mans true director alone, without all their made Faiths, and framed Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectories, or any ſuch thing. And we do further be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, That 'tis not the Common-Prayer-Book, nor the Sprinkling of Children, or any thing elſe that they can invent that will make a Man or a Woman a new Creature, but Chriſt, which is the true Bread which cometh down from Heaven, they that eat thereof ſhall never Hunger more; and Chriſt hath promiſed this to them which hunger after Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; they that hunger after Righteouſneſs Chriſt is feeding with this Bread, and he is chuſing of them out of the Vanities of this World. But they that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the leading and guiding of the Spirit of God, and ſay, <hi>That Inſpiration and Revelation is ceaſed,</hi> as the Prieſts and Profeſſors do, and ſay, <hi>There is no ſuch thing now adayes.</hi> Such never come to eat of that Bread, which Chriſt ſaid he would give to them that hungred after him; but them that are Full and Rich he ſendeth
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:36615:34"/>empty away, but the Needy and poor of Spirit he Feedeth and filleth with good things.</p>
            <p>But as to them that deny <hi>Revelation</hi> and the <hi>Light of Chriſt,</hi> which enlightneth all, and the Righteous are guided by, them that oppoſe and deny this, I do believe that they ſee no Revelation, neither do they ſee any Beauty or Comlineſs in the appearance of Chriſt, for he is grieved in them as a man of Sorrows, and his Viſage is more marred by them then any mans, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are alwayes Warring, Writing, and envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly Oppoſing the Light and Spirit of God in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and in others.</p>
            <p>Therefore they muſt needs not know how it is with them, and muſt needs be blind while they are in ſtriving againſt that which would let them ſee; for the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith, <hi>There is none knoweth the things of God but by the Spirit of God.</hi> And in this ſtate and condition, rebelling againſt that which is the only means of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and are mudling in the dark, and know not how it is with them, becauſe they are hearken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the falſe Prophets and blind Guides; and this is the reaſon that Condemnation is come upon them that are condemned, becauſe Chriſt is come, &amp; they that will not believe on him muſt be condemned; <hi>This being the Condemnation of the World, that Light is come into the world &amp; men love Darkneſs rather then Light becauſe their Deeds are Evil.</hi> For we may read that whilſt <hi>Paul</hi> was oppoſing of the Light and Spirit in himſelf, which often times pricked him in his Conſcience for what he did, which was not right, although it were in a blind Zeal, and under a cover of Religion, yet being done in his own Will, and according to the Wiſdom
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:36615:34"/>of the Fleſh, this was that which blinded his Eye that he could not ſee how it was with him, but was as theſe be now adayes, hating and perſecuting of the Juſt, and yet talking much of Religion, and very buſie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Letter, talking much of the Prophets Words, but Perſecuting the Juſt, and quenching the Spirit of Chriſt, as theſe outſide Profeſſors do now adayes: So we may ſee that <hi>Paul,</hi> till he came to know Revelation in himſelf, and to walk by the Light of Chriſt which ſhone in him, for all his Learning and his great Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet he was ignorant of the Way of the Lord; and as to his own Condition, he could not examine himſelf, nor know how it was with him, till he tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to that which reproved him, and ſo to have his mind guided by it, and his Converſation to be mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by that which pricked his Conſcience, and ſo he came to fear the Lord more then men; and though men roſe up againſt him for coming to that ſtrange Doctrine, as they ſo called it, which Doctrine the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of this World could never underſtand in that Age, neither can they now, but alwayes counted it ſtrange, Madneſs and Folly; and ſo they do now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, and when <hi>Paul</hi> came to be led by another Spirit then that he was led by, or then that they were led by, &amp; by this he came to be led beyond their <hi>wiſdom,</hi> then they cryed out he was a Mad Man; and ſo they are crying now adayes concerning us, becauſe as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>They know not what they do, nor what Spirit they are of;</hi> and thus the Blind leadeth the Blind.</p>
            <p>And here lieth the reaſon there is ſo much Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion among men about Religion, and why ſo few are choſen, becauſe they go from the true Guide, and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:36615:35"/>from him that giveth a right underſtanding con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the true Worſhip, and things relating to Salvation.</p>
            <p>For there is no other Name given under Heaven, whereby any man comes to the Kingdom of Heaven and is ſaved, but by Chriſt Jeſus alone; for as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I am the Way, the Truth and the Life,</hi> John 14.6. Now to this moſt People of all ſorts will confeſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is Scripture, that Chriſt is the Way, the Truth and the Life.</p>
            <p>But now here is one thing to be conſidered, that I would have all People well to mind, that is, Chriſt being the Way, the Truth and the Life, to know what Way he is, and how he is the Truth and the Life: Now to confeſs to this is one thing, and to come to be a Witneſs of it is another thing; for mind Chriſt, his mind in this thing is, that he is man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Way to Heaven, and the Truth that they muſt come to and be guided by, and the Life that they muſt live in, which is by Faith in the Son of God. Now here lieth the matter to be conſidered, whether or no thou art come to that ſtate and condition, that is, to come to know Chriſt to be thy Way? and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou art come to know the Truth as it is in Jeſus? and to live that Life which pleaſes God, yea or nay? which Life is in Chriſt Jeſus; this every one is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider; for till People come to be Witneſſes of this in themſelves, 'tis not a confeſſing to it or talking of it will do or ſtand them in any ſtead in the Day of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, when God comes to reckon with them.</p>
            <p>For this the holy men of God did witneſs, and ſaid, <hi>The Life which we now live is by the Faith of the Son of God,</hi> Gal. 2.20.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:36615:35"/>
            <p>And <hi>John</hi> ſaid (that came to witneſs the work of God begun, and carrying on in himſelf) on this manner, <hi>That which was from the beginning, which we have heard, which we have ſeen with our Eyes, which we have looked upon, and our Hands have handled of the Word of Life, this declare we unto you,</hi> 1 John 1.1. And further the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Chriſt wrought all their Works in them and for them;</hi> which work was to root out Sin.</p>
            <p>Now this they came to know and witneſs in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and not by report and hear-ſay of others; this ſtate the People of God came to in all Ages and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, in a meaſure while they were here in this Life, and did not think to have the work of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion done for them when they were dead, as ſome now adayes think to have, thinking to ſerve the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil while they are here, and that God will ſave them when they can ſin no longer: but mark this, ſuch as People ſow, ſuch ſhall they reap, and they that ſow Sin and Wickedneſs, muſt of the ſame Wages reap Corruption, which Wages the Scripture ſaith is Death, ſaying, <hi>The Wages of Sin is Death,</hi> (and that to them for evermore) <hi>but the Gift of God is Eternal Life,</hi> Rom. 6.23. For this is a ſtrange thing that a man ſhould be a Servant to one man many Years, and at laſt come to another for Wages for the ſame time; this is Confuſion and Madneſs, and with this Cheat a great part of the World is cheated by both Prieſts and Profeſſors, in telling People that they cannot live without Sin, and ſo they ſerve the Devil all their days, and that God would accept with the reward of Peace of them, when they can ſerve him no longer: For inaſmuch as they tell People, they cannot leave off
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:36615:36"/>Sinning, but muſt ſin as long as they live; it is the ſame thing as if they tell People, they muſt ſerve the Devil all their dayes; for there is no ſin committed or brought forth in any, but it is of the Devil's beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and bringing forth in People; for he is the Father of all Sin in all people, whereſoever or in whomſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it is brought forth; and therefore this unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably muſt follow, that they that live and dye in Sin, muſt live and dye Servants to the Devil; &amp; if ſo, every man muſt expect his Wages according to his Works: Therefore I would have none deceive themſelves, for if the Devil muſt be ſerved all your dayes, him you muſt go to at laſt unavoidably, whether you will believe it or no.</p>
            <p>And further, take notice of this; Chriſt is not the Way of the Wicked, nor of Sinners, neither are Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, or they that plead for Sin, come to the Truth, nor to know it, nor to live the Life of it, which Life is out of Sin, and not in Sin, for that is a Life of the Devil; for he is the Founder of all Sin, and the Wages of Sin is Death and Damnation to all that live and dye in Sin. Theſe things are worthy to be conſidered before it be too late, which will be when God's Spirit hath done ſtriving with thee; for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out coming to know the Devil's Works deſtroyed in thee, or that work begun by the Lord, till thou comeſt to know this, thou ſhalt never know the Truth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Free from Sin, and that which makes Free from ſin is Chriſt; and till People come to know this Freedom from Sin begun, they can never know Righteouſneſs; and without Righteouſneſs, none ſhall ſee God, and without coming to ſee God; none can
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:36615:36"/>go to Heaven; till they come to be Freed from Sin, none can be fitted for Heaven. And the Scripture ſaith, <hi>The Truth makes Free;</hi> and the Truth is Chriſt Jeſus; and if this be to make Free, it is to make Free from ſomething; and if it be not from Sin, what is it that People muſt be Freed from? I would know; I do believe it is from Sin; for I never heard of any thing that any was in Bondage to but Sin, that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth People of Salvation; and therefore Chriſt the Truth is come to make an end of it, that Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs may reign in the room of Sin; and theſe two things were never known to dwell together, but one muſt be known to be pulling down before the other can be ſet up; therefore it was ſaid, <hi>Light hath no fellowſhip with Darkneſs, nor a Believer with an Infidel.</hi> Here Chriſt is meant the Light, and the Devil the Power of Darkneſs; and theſe two War one againſt the other in People, ſtriving which ſhall rule and bear ſway in Peoples Minds, Hearts and Affections: one of theſe two Spirits ſtriveth to lead into all manner of Sin and Evil; and the other ſtriveth to lead into all manner of Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs, both in things Spiritual and Temporal.</p>
            <p>And here I will make a difference betwixt the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of their working and ſtriving in People, and that in all People at one time or another, and that all may be ſenſible of it, if they will; but if they will not in the day when God's good Spirit ſtriveth with them, they ſhall be brought one day to a Remembrance of it, when they ſhall be unwilling, and before they are aware, when nothing but Death and Sorrow ſhall meet together, and none to help them will be found.</p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:36615:37"/>
            <p>Now to the matter and manner of theſe two Spirits ſtriving: the bad Spirit, he in all People ſtrives to keep their Minds altogether in Carnal and in Earthly things, which is Death to the Soul: The Scripture ſaith, <hi>To be Carnally-minded is Death, but to be Spiritually-minded is Life and Peace:</hi> and this I do believe is true; I have found it ſo by good Experience.</p>
            <p>And this is the Devils end to keep Peoples Minds up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earthly things, that they may never mind Heavenly things, but to ſpend away their precious time in this <hi>world,</hi> till there be no more time, that thereby they may loſe the <hi>Treaſure</hi> in Heaven, that is laid up in Heaven for all thoſe that will come to God upon his Terms, which Terms are for People to Repent, deny themſelves, to take up a Croſs to their own Wills, to love and fear God, and to worſhip him in Spirit and Truth; and I am ſure that none can do this without the Spirit, if it muſt be as the Scripture ſaith, in the Spirit and in the Truth; and I believe the Scripture is true, and that Chriſt ſpoke true when he ſpoke theſe words, and all prieſts and Profeſſors are in Error and Blindneſs that deny theſe things: but all them that love the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus, which is the chief Terms of Salvation, come to know Benefit thereby; the manner of his appearing is in Peoples Minds againſt Sin; and they that love that which the Spirit of God appeareth againſt, and judgeth in their Minds, they are yet hating of God, let them profeſs what they will, it is in vain; but they that love thoſe things which the Spirit of God in themſelves appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for, theſe be they that love his Appearance.</p>
            <p>But in all Ages, they that had got on a Covering,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:36615:37"/>which was not of God's Spirit, theſe were ever the work; for all Religions are falſe, except that in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Truth; and all theſe falſe Colours of Religion were ever invented by the Devil; and this is one way that he in all Generations did work, when he could no longer keep People in open Prophaneneſs, then he invents new wayes for them to walk in, and he will plead Scripture for it too, and ſpeak much of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men of God's Works too, That in Ages paſt they were commanded to do, which were good in their Day and Time to them that were obedient to it, which were to laſt till Chriſt the Subſtance came, or till the time of Reformation, being but Shadows and Figures of the Subſtance, which bleſſed be the Lord he is come, and hath put an end to theſe things, and hath ſet up a Worſhip in Spirit and Truth. But the Spirit of the Devil he is alwayes a keeping buſied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout outward things and Lip-ſervice, that he may keep the Heart upon ſome viſible thing, and off from the inward and ſpiritual Worſhip; and this is one way that he worketh in the Myſtery of Iniquity: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes when he can keep People no longer in open Prophaneneſs, then to turn them into outward Duties, as he calls them, when God required no ſuch thing at their Hands; for it is firſt the Heart the Lord requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, ſaying, <hi>My Son,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 23.26.</note> 
               <hi>give me thy Heart:</hi> that is, to ſet their Hearts on the Lord, and to be led by his good Spirit in them, then Family-Duties and other Duties are by God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, they being done by the Guidance of Gods good Spirit; for thou mayſt read in the Scriptures of Truth (which we own, and have more eſteem of them
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:36615:38"/>than any other Book in the World) and they ſpeak after this manner; ſaying, <hi>The Prayers of the Wicked are Abomination to the Lord; but the Prayers of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous avail much.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Manner of the Spirit of the Devil is to keep People from being Righteous, that their Prayers may not be accepted; and keeping in outward things, that they may never know the inward Work of God, which is to work out Sin, and to bring in Everlaſting Righteouſneſs. But he is keeping of them ever hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ever learning, that they may never be able to come to the Knowledge of the Truth; for he knows, while they are hear kening to the Teaching of the blind Guides, they can never come to the Knowledge of the Truth; for the Devil knows, till People come to be led and guided by the Spirit of Truth it is impoſſible that they can ever come to the Knowledge of the Truth: here he keeps People ſeeking of the Living amongſt the Dead, and Life where no Life is: And this is the manner of the working of the Enemy.</p>
            <p>And this is the greateſt Cheat that the Devil hath to cheat People of their Souls, to turn People into one Outſide Painted Religion or another, and then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them all is well; and moſt of them are willing to believe him, it being in the Delightſome Tract of the World, only differing in ſome Geremonies; but the Religion in Spirit and Truth, Light and Grace, this the Profeſſors cannot abide, becauſe it calls into a Narrow Way, and to enter in at a ſtrait Gate.</p>
            <p>For the Enemy had rather, or as lieve People got into ſome Tract or Form of Religion, as not, for then he can perſwade them it is well with them, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:36615:38"/>them that they need not ſeek after any thing elſe; and all this he doth, that he may keep them from the true Worſhip in Spirit and Truth. But thoſe that are in open Prophaneneſs he cannot blind after this Manner; for they know, whoſoever is Right they are Wrong, and have no Cover for what they do; therefore Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Publicans and Harlots ſhould enter the Kingdom of Heaven before ſuch as Profeſs Service to God, and ſerve him not acceptably;</hi> for no Service is acceptable, but that in Spirit and Truth: <hi>We unto them that are Covered, and not with the Spirit of the Lord.</hi> And many more Wayes the Devil hath to keep People from anſwering the Requirings of God's Spirit, but no Snare like to a Falſe Cover of Religion.</p>
            <p>Many there be that he hath other Baits for, that matter nothing of any Religion; ſome he keeps all their dayes their Minds and Hearts in Covetouſneſs, ſome in Pride, ſome in Drunkenneſs, ſome in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zening and Cheating; and many more Baits and Snares he hath to betray People of their Happineſs with the Lord: ſome the Devil perſwades, they ſhall never give an Account to God for what they do, and ſo live like Ranters all their dayes: And he tells them, There is neither God nor Devil, Hell nor Heaven, and many are willing to believe it: But have a care of this Perſwaſion; for thou ſhalt know theſe things to be Lyes one day, to the Sorrow of thy Soul, when it will be too late for thee to conſider, if thou doſt not Repent in time. Others the Devil perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, that God hath created ſome to <hi>Salvation,</hi> others to <hi>Damnation,</hi> which is as great an Untruth as the other, and a great many are willing to believe it, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:36615:39"/>they are of thoſe that are ordain'd to Salvation; ſome others there be of that mind that are perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that if it be ſo, they are of that Number which are born to Damnation; and upon this Perſwaſion many grow Careleſs in their Converſations, and run into all manner of Evil. This Perſwaſion is a juſt Road to Deſtruction, and a Sink of Iniquity, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes many a poor Soul.</p>
            <p>All theſe things that I have mentioned, and many more which might be mentioned, are the Wayes and Inventions which the Devil hath invented and ſet up in and among People; and this is his manner of working by his Spirit in People, and yet pleads Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for what he doth, that thereby he might colour over his Deceit. And this hath been his manner in all Ages to deceive the Nations of the World; but Wo be to them that hearken to him: this is the Strangers Voice, which Chriſt ſaid, <hi>his Sheep would not hearken to;</hi> ſaying, <hi>My Sheep here my Voice, and the Voice of a Stranger will they not hear.</hi> Here it it doth appear there were two Voices to be heard; here was the Voice of Chriſt, and the Strangers Voice, which was the Voice of the Devil: Theſe two Voices now adayes are heard, and are obeyed by all People, either the one or the other; for none can ſerve two Maſters, or obey two Voices; therefore People cannot ſerve God and Mamon: And the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of theſe two Spirits uttering their Voices is in an Inviſible and Spiritual manner.</p>
            <p>And as I have before opened the Myſteries of Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, &amp; the manner of the Working of the Spirit of the Enemy, ſo now I am come to relate how, and in what
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:36615:39"/>manner doth the Spirit of the Lord differ in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of working from the Spirit of the Devil in all People, at one time or another; this is known ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in them, though they will not obey it that is of this manner; it doth begin to work, to knock at the Door of Peoples Hearts, or ſecretly reprove for Sin, trouble People for doing that which they ought not to do, and condemns them when they do amiſs; this is calledin the Scriptures, the Reproofs of Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the Way of Life; and I do believe it is ſo, although many Profeſſors will not believe it; and if it be the Way of Life, I do believe it is able to Redeem from that it calls out of, which is Sin and Wickedneſs, and as People hearken to it, it opens their Underſtandings, and ſheweth them how it is with them, and not only ſo, but bringeth into a New Life and Converſation, and keeps Peoples Minds al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in that which is Good, and out of that which is Bad; and this is as Spiritual Food for the Soul, and then People come to know that Bread which comes down from Heaven, and to drink of that Water that never faileth; and brings that Peace upon People, which none can know, but them that do enjoy it: This doth the Light or Spirit of God do in the Righteous, and much more which might be mentioned: This is he that the Scripture calls, <hi>The Searcher of Hearts, and a Tryer of Reins;</hi> he is a Juſtifier of the Righteous, and a Condemner of the Wicked; and to him muſt all give an Account one day. After this manner doth the Spirit of the Lord differ from the Spirit of the Devil, in operating and working in People; and one of theſe leads to Heaven, and the other to Hell.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:36615:40"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:36615:40"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:36615:41"/>
            <p>Here is one thing more which comes in my Mind concerning the working of theſe two Spirits; the Spirit of the Lord many times by often following and purſuing of People with his Righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, till he brings to a Conſideration of their Lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter End, and then many times in that Condition peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple come to ſeek after the right Way, and then the Lord openeth the Myſteries of his Kingdom to them, and then they begin to fee the Right Way from the Wrong, the Narrow Way from the Wide, and begin to ſee the Gate to be ſtrait, and the Way to be narrow; then many begin to conſult with the Reaſoning Part in Man, which is the Work of the Enemy; for he makes it his Buſineſs at all times to work out all that is good; his manner is, when any come to be convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of the Right Way, then to ſet them into que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioning, <hi>How they ſhall enter in at this ſtrait Gate, and to walk in that narrow Way,</hi> and ſo come to ſeek after ſome eaſier Way; and the Devil he ſets all manner of Dangers before people, and begins to tell them, <hi>That the way is too hard for them to walk in;</hi> and tells them, <hi>There be many eaſier and better Wayes, wherein they may walk and do well;</hi> and tells them, <hi>That is the Worſt Way of all, any thing but that;</hi> for he knows well enough, there is no other Way to Heaven: and ſaith the Enemy, <hi>If thou owneſt this Worſhip in Spirit, thou wilt be hated of all people, and in Danger of loſing all, and of having the Diſpleaſure of this or the other Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Neighbour or Acquaintance;</hi> and ſaith he, <hi>This is a new Upſtart Religion, hath been but lately ſtanding; and</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>our Religion hath been long ſtanding, and our Mother-Church cannot Err;</hi> and ſaith he, <hi>our Fore-Fathers
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:36615:41"/>were in the Right, and our Miniſters, who have great Learning, muſt be in the Right, or elſe who can be Right? and how can Tradeſmen, Plowmen and ſuch come to know the Way to Heaven?</hi> Theſe things and many more the Devil puts into peoples Minds, to ſet them againſt that which would ſave their Souls, that when God hath called people by his Spirit to walk in the Narrow Way, which leadeth to Everlaſting Life, then the Devil he muſters up all theſe fore-mentioned things, and many more which might be mentioned, and layes before people as Snares, and by this many times turns people ſome one way and ſome another, any way ſo that they might not come to walk in the Narrow Way, and to worſhip God in Spirit and Truth; ſome he turneth into Fears, <hi>how they ſhall live;</hi> ſome into the Mire and Dirt of Sin and Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs again; ſome under Falſe Colours of Religions; ſome into Careleſneſs; ſome into Diſpair, and tells them, <hi>Their Day is over;</hi> others he tells, <hi>There is time enough yet to Repent,</hi> and ſo lulls people aſleep in Sin till there is no more time; &amp; others he upbraids with the Unfaithfulneſs of ſome who profeſs the Truth; but Wo be to them that hearken to him in any kind, mark this, <hi>Thou ſhalt anſwer for what thou doſt, and ſo ſhall others for themſelves;</hi> and further, <hi>Whatſoever o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers do, that will be no Excuſe for thee in the Day of Account.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore have a care of believing the lying Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, which with his Lyes and Deceit goeth about to deceive the Nations, and moſt people are deceived by him; and becauſe people are hearkening to him more than to the Lord, this is the Reaſon ſo few are choſen
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:36615:42"/>of the Number that are called; <hi>for many are Called, but few are Choſen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would not have people think it ſtrange as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this manner of Reaſoning that is put into peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by the Devil, I would have none ſhould think hard of this; for I will tell thee plainly, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is put into any Man or Woman's Mind, that is not right, true or good, is put in by the ſpirit of the Devil; and whatſoever is put into any Man or Woman's Mind that is good, right and juſt, is done by the Spirit of the Lord; for take notice of this, all peoples Minds and Affections are ſwayed by one or the other of theſe two Spirits, one turning into Wickedneſs, the other into Righteouſneſs; this is true, whether thou wilt believe it or no, thou ſhalt be made to know it when it will be too late, if thou art not aware.</p>
            <p>A few words in anſwer to the fore-mentioned Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings and Objections againſt the Truth and Spiritual Worſhip.</p>
            <p>As to the Strait Gate and Narrow Way, it is ſtrait to the Wicked, it is pleaſant to the Righteous; and as to the many Wayes, there are not many Wayes to Heaven, but to Heaven there is but one Way, and that is to come to anſwer God's Spirit in thee, and to worſhip God in Spirit and in Truth.</p>
            <p>And as to the being hated of all people, this is no new thing; for Chriſt and all the holy Men of God were ever Hated, as thou mayſt read in the Scriptures; and <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, <hi>He did eſteem of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preaches that be under-went for Chriſt's ſake to be greater Riches to him than all the Treaſures in</hi> Egypt: and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:36615:42"/>though they were hated of Men, yet they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of God; and all this while it is well enough.</p>
            <p>And as to the Danger of Loſing any thing for Chriſt's ſake, this was counted by the Righteous all Joy, that they were not counted only worthy to Rain with Chriſt, but alſo to Suffer with him; and the Lord hath promiſed, <hi>That whatſoever any Suffer for him, they ſhall have Recompenſed in this Life a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fold, and in the World to come Life Everlaſting,</hi> without End. And the Scripture ſaith, <hi>They that will live Godly in Chriſt Jeſus, muſt ſuffer Perſecutions.</hi> And Chriſt told his Diſciples, <hi>The Servant was not greater than his Maſter; if they perſecuted him, it was certain they would perſeoute them.</hi> And as to the Diſpleaſing of Men, it is impoſſible that people can pleaſe God and Ungodly Men; and <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> bad people <hi>judge whether they had beſt Pleaſe God or Man.</hi> And as concerning a Livelihood, believe the Scripture, <hi>Firſt ſeek God's Kingdom, and the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs thereof, and all other things ſhall be added to thee,</hi> Matth. 6.33.</p>
            <p>And as for our Religion, which is in Spirit and in Truth, to be a <hi>New Upſtart Religion,</hi> this is a down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Slander; for it was ſet up by Chriſt above ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen hundred years ago; and there is no other Way to Heaven but this; though ſome there be that do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs it, that do not walk in it, this doth not alter the Caſe, or make the thing not to be the ſame as it is profeſſed; for <hi>Judas</hi> did not alter the Caſe in that matter, neither do any Traitors to the Truth now adayes.</p>
            <p>And as to the Falſe Religion, it is true it hath been
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:36615:43"/>long ſtanding, the more is the Pity; yet that doth not make, becauſe Falſe Religions have been long ſtanding, that therefore it muſt ever remain; this will not hold. It is true, ever ſince Wickedneſs hath been covered under a Cloak of Religion, this hath been ſtanding.</p>
            <p>And as to the Church, which ſome ſay <hi>cannot Err:</hi> I anſwer, that there is no Church or People but do Err, except them that are led and guided by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, and ſuch are the only true Church; and they that are led by this, are led by that Spirit that never did nor can Err: and till people come to this, all go aſtray, let them profeſs what they will.</p>
            <p>And as to our Fore-Fathers, how it was with them, that I will leave to the Lord; I will not judge of them that I never knew: but this I do believe of them, That ſome of them were Faithful to what they knew, and that is it the Lord requires, and doth accept of; and as to them, they are gone, and I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve ſome of them dyed in the true Faith, which we do believe in; and I do believe, they are at Reſt with the Lord, and were of our Mind and Belief, though not called by this new Nick-Name, which the Devil in our Age hath invented for his Servants to put upon us, as in all Ages the Devil had New Nick-Names for to diſguiſe and deride Chriſt and his Followers, and ſo he hath now.</p>
            <p>And for your Miniſters to know the Way, there are none that know the Truth, nor no true Miniſters, but them that come to be endewed with Power from on High, which is known by Revelation and Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which your Prieſts and Profeſſors do deny; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:36615:43"/>they cannot know the Truth while they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying that which bringeth to the Knowledge of the Truth; for the Scripture ſaith, (and I do believe they are true, and they ſay) though <hi>there is a Spirit in Man, yet it is the Inſpiration of the Almighty that gives an Underſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as concerning Great Learning, this is good in its place, as men come to the true Underſtanding of it given to them by the Spirit of God; for the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is as a Myſtery hid from the Wiſdom of this World; and it was never known that Outward Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or Education of Men, nor Great Learning, did ever bring any man to the Knowledge of the Truth, nor never was able to unſold the Myſtery of Godlineſs to any man; as for Inſtance, there was <hi>Paul,</hi> he was a great Learned Man, and had great Parts and Education, and counted himſelf beyond many of the <hi>Jews,</hi> yet for all this he was ignorant of the true Knowledge of God, till he came to it by the Revelation of the Son of God; for that was and now is the thing alone that brought People to the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of that which is hid from the Wiſdom of this World.</p>
            <p>And as concerning Tradeſmen and Plowmen knowing the Way, read the Scriptures, and there thou wilt find in all Ages it was ſuch chiefly that came to the true Knowledge of the right Way of God, for there were <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> that were Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned Men, and many more beſide them, which were able Miniſters of the Lord; and where are there any great Learned Men now adayes that can compare with them? but there are many now adayes
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:36615:44"/>that are come to the Knowledge of the Truth as they came to it by the Learning which they have lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the Lord, ſo do they preach, whether they have outward Learning or not, this makes not much matter in the things of God, though Learning be very good in its place to them that make good uſe of it; but if you obſerve the greateſt Learned Men are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly moſt ignorant of Chriſt's Kingdom; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that is not the thing that makes people Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous; nor is it enough barely reading the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets Words and Works, and Chriſt's Words, and what he did, and the Apoſtles Conditions, how it was with them, it is not enough to read theſe things, unleſs people come to live the ſame Life that they did, but it muſt be done by the Power of God; and this is the Reaſon that there are ſo many ever reading and hearing, and never able to come to the Knowledge of the Truth, thinking by running into outward things they ſhall do well, and never come to Chriſt that they may know Life Eternal, which is <hi>to know God,</hi> as the Scripture ſaith) <hi>whom to know is Life Eternal,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Day and a Time hath God given to all people, that if they will in that Day and Time they may come to know God, and by him to be cleanſed of Sin, which is the Cauſe of Death to their Souls.</p>
            <p>And in this Day Chriſt would gather all People to himſelf as a Hen gathers her Chickens under her Wings; but if people will not come to him in that Day and Time, when he calleth to them, they ſhall never know Freedom from the Bondage of Hell and Death.</p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:36615:44"/>
            <p>A Lamentation may be taken up concerning all ſuch, that ſin out their Day, and the Night comes on them at unawares, and there be none to help, as Chriſt took up concerning <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when their Day was over, he went and beheld it with much Sorrow, and wept over it with much Pity, ſaying on this wiſe, <hi>O</hi> Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem! <hi>thou that killeſt the Prophets, and ſtoneſt them that are ſent to thee; how often would I have gathered thee, even as a Hen would have gathered her Chickens under her Wings, and ye would not!</hi> and further ſaid he, <hi>O that thou hadſt known in this thy Day the things belonging to thy Peace! but now they are hid from thine Eyes.</hi> So it is with all people that ſin out their Day as they did; for the Lord ſtriveth with all People, as well as he ſtrove with them, to bring them to the Knowledge of the Things that belong to their Peace; but ſtill here they lie in Ignorance, not yielding to the Motions of the Spirit of Chriſt, although there be things laid up in ſtore for them, which do belong to their Peace; yet in this Condition they are never worthy to know it, becauſe they believe not; and they that are not faithful in a little, never come to know much.</p>
            <p>Thus will it be with all thoſe that ſin out their Day, and will not anſwer God in the Time when he ſtriveth with them.</p>
            <p>So 'tis good for all people to conſider theſe things, before it be too late, that they may get Aſſurance of that which will ſtand by them, and make choice of that which <hi>Mary</hi> did, that Good Part which ſhall never be taken from them; and herein people will come to finiſh their courſe with Joy, and lay down
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:36615:45"/>their Heads in Peace when Dayes and Time ſhall be no more.</p>
            <p>Thus far have I cleared my Conſcience of that which lay upon me from the Lord to write, in Love to all who deſire to be in Favour with God, that they may have Aſſurance of Acceptance with him for their Souls, when their Bodies muſt be laid in their Graves.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>So I reſt, with Love and Good Will towards all People, deſiring the Good and Proſperity of all in that Way which leadeth to that Kingdom which is not of this World, who am known to many to be of that Mind and of that Deſire, by the Name of</hi> John Songhurſt.</signed>
               <dateline>Weſt Chiltington <hi>in</hi> Suſſex, <date>
                     <hi>in the 2d Moneth,</hi> 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
